Call the meeting to order and the superintendent will take the roll.
DeAngelis.
Here.
Feller.
Holman.
Here.
Richardson.
Rish.
Here.
Smith.
Cabissa.
Here.
Davidson.
And anyone who would like to stand and join us for the pledge of allegiance
is invited to do so, but not required.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for which it stands,
one nation under God, indivisible, with
liberty and justice for all.
And
justice.
You said that?
Mm-hmm.
And justice.
As this is a public proceeding, unless the Board of Education specifically
votes to enter into executive session-
Oh, yeah.
Oh, boy.
Thank you.
Sorry. Over there. I got it.
Unless the Board of Education specifically votes to enter into executive
session, the public has the right to hear everything and to look at all
exhibits. Please let us know if you experience difficulties with
accessibility, as there are members of the district staff located
in the lecture hall,
and they can provide assistance. The school board works from a prepared
agenda, which is posted in advance on the district website, and
printed copies of this evening's agenda are available near the
entrance to the lecture hall.
Fellow board members are reminded that Robert's Rules states
members may speak no more than twice on the same question at any one meeting,
except by permission of the chair.
Questions, brief suggestions, or points of clarification are not
counted as speaking in debate. The board asks that the public audience refrain
from clapping. Although tonight, we're going to clap for these young men here in
the front.
From clapping, booing, or side comments or other behaviors that could interrupt the
flow of speakers. And every person is entitled to speak their opinion and feel
safe in the process.
So I will first make a couple announcements
that this board accepts the resignation of Vice Chair Adrian Dowling,
and I want to thank Mr. Dowling for his work on this school board.
He served as a member who was thoughtful, aware, informed, and
always prepared. And additionally, in his role as vice chair,
he was an immense resource, a listening ear, and a
person who was trusted and valued.
We will elect a new vice chair later in this meeting.
The following dates
are important to note. There's
a
city council budget workshop tomorrow night
at 6:30, April 14th, which is at City Hall
Chambers, and there's a special board meeting Wednesday,
April 29th, here in the lecture hall at six o'clock,
and there's a regular meeting at 6:00 PM Monday, May
11th, in the lecture hall.
Following that, I wanted to say there has been lots of feedback
from parents and educators, and I want people to know we're listening.
We will have an action item on the agenda on April
29th to halt the movement towards
reconfiguration to move forward for this
September
2026.
And we will
halt that reconfiguration at this time.
There is strong support on this school board to delay the action,
and the decision to do this on April 29th is to allow
for sufficient public notice and to afford time to write the
action item correctly. However, it is clear that this board
supports that delay, and we sincerely appreciate your concerns.
Please know, first, that this board knows only what you
know, and there are no side meetings or efforts to move
things forward that do not occur in public.
I had a two-and-a-half-hour talk with a constituent today, and it's
clear to me, and to others on this board, that slowing down is what's
best for all.
Our goal now is to find ways to come together, to work together, and
to plan together. I trust we can do that.
The Reconfiguration Committee will continue to
move forward, and the board will have two representatives.
I have asked Board Member Smith and Board Member Richardson to serve on
that committee, and both have agreed.
I think they will represent this board well, and we are grateful for the time and
effort they will surely put into that work.
While we had two votes in opposition to reconfiguration,
both members, Feller and Richardson, have committed to believing that
this model will best serve our students, so they will help us to
move that forward for the following year.
With an additional timeline, we believe we can satisfy the anxieties
of everyone involved.
Our focus at this juncture is on Kaylor staff and
students. Let's come together and support them with the goal
of helping transitions to happen as smoothly and effectively as
possible.Showing kindness to all of them and helping in
every way we can is the beginning. Again, I believe we can
do that, too. Thank you for giving your attention to Kaylor and that
community. Their loss is real, which means our loss is
real. Thank you.
So we will go next to the nomination of the
vice chair.
And I would-
That's just an info.
Oh, that's-
There's an action item later
... action item later. Okay.
Yes.
So we'll do that action item later.
So that's the nomination of the vice chair, and
next is the report of the student representative,
Angela-
All right
... Ebisa.
Thank you.
Good evening, everyone. I hope everyone's doing well tonight.
Despite all the many events and learning experiences happening across the district,
the South Portland School Department continues to see strong engagement,
achievement, and positive school communities.
Starting off at the elementary schools, at Brown School, their spring season
of Girls on the Run is underway with 22 students and five dedicated
coaches. They are grateful for the staff members who volunteer their time
to support this program, which promotes confidence, teamwork, and healthy
habits.
Students are also benefiting from learning beyond the classroom, including a recent
first grade field trip to the planetarium as a part of an
interdisciplinary unit.
They are also looking forward to an upcoming author visit from Ralph
III for all elementary grade levels.
In addition, Brown School classrooms have earned over 300 golden tickets
for demonstrating safe, respectful, and responsible behavior,
celebrating together with class rewards that help strengthen positive school
culture.
And at Dyer Elementary School, students recently completed their
readathon with 200,000 minutes read,
reflecting a strong commitment to literacy across the school.
They are now preparing for their upcoming character parade, where students will
dress as book characters alongside their classmates, with families invited to
attend the celebration.
And moving on to Kaylor, students in grades two to
four recently welcomed Crusher, the Maine Celtics mascot,
alongside with his partner, and students participated in engaging
community activities focused on healthy lifestyles, teamwork,
basketball skills, including jump shots and layups, in a fun and
interactive school experience.
At Skillin, students participated in a strong month
literacy-focused activity, including weekly drop everything and read
sessions and a mystery reader event featuring surprise
guests. They have also hosted a successful family
literacy and math night with hands-on activities for students and
families.
The month concluded with a community celebration honoring Principal Connolly,
who received the Maine Association of School Libraries Administration of the Year
award.
At Small Elementary, students read over 130,000
minutes during the readathon and celebrated with a school-wide assembly and dance
party.
The celebration included students honoring teachers in creative ways, such as pie
in the face, coloring hair, and gift wrapping.
They have also launched their Girls on the Run program, supporting students in
building confidence, fitness, and friendships through structured, goal-oriented
activities.
At South Portland Middle School, students and staff are looking forward to
several upcoming spring events, including the staff talent show on April 30th
and World Cultures Day on May 6th, and staff will continue to
focus on collaborative instructional planning and engaging students in
meaningful hands-on learning experience.
Lastly, at South Portland High School, students recently performed the musical
"Chicago," and it was amazing. I attended it yesterday.
They have also held a family teacher conference, 11th grade
testing, a college information night, and this week, we are actually
hosting community week, which celebrates the diverse identities,
cultures, and experience within the school through spirit days, performances,
athletics, guest speakers, and wellness activities. Thank you.
Thank you, Angela. And
next we have the recognition of the Maine Association of School Libraries
Administrator of the Year.
So I'm going to turn to you for that,
Superintendent Entwistle.
Okay.
Let's see here.
My slides have disappeared.
Yeah.
I do too sometimes.
Okay.
There you go.
Thank you,
Claire. Appreciate that.
Catch up now, here.
Okay, just a quick review of the norms of the school board.
I did a more extensive review last time,
in advance of that meeting. The meeting went really well.
This is really just a reminder, thinking about things,
as participants, and we're all participants here and there.
Thinking about active listening,
making sure that we're acknowledging contributions,
other people's work, showing empathy, trying to identify and be
mindful of feelings,
attempting to be mindful of the value of every individual.
Civility, of course, very important.
Respecting other people's boundaries and privacy, and treating them
with kindness.
And lastly, avoiding premature judgment and always
presuming good intent with the folks that you're
interacting with.
Thank you.
So, umTonight, I
just want to speak first a little bit about the agenda itself.
We've got some great recognition happening.
I thought there was going to be 60 students, but I'm
happy to see all of the boys that have
showed up today, and we will be celebrating them.
As well, the board needs to engage in some dialogue related
to financial guidance that they'll be seeking tomorrow night from the city
council. It's important business and needs
to have some time spent on that. For these reasons,
I would like to recommend to the board that they again modify the public comment
rules for tonight as they did earlier to include
three minute person time allowance,
enabling those new speakers who've not had a chance to speak to
get to the front of the line, and a maximum of between 60 and
75 minutes for each of the two sessions.
That will require a vote of the board, and
that's up to them.
I do want to talk a little bit about
the
2026 Maine Association of School Libraries, which is
MASL,
Administrator of the Year.
And Bethany Colony,
sorry, Bethany
Conley, principal at Skillen Elementary School, has been named
the 26th
Administrator of the Year. The award was presented at a special
all-school assembly on March 27th.
I understand that was a surprise to her
as well, and that's kind of exciting.
Bethany was nominated by Skillen
Elementary School librarian, Jennifer Stanbro, and
supported by numerous administrators and teachers who cited her exceptional
support for the school's library program.
The nomination highlighted Bethany's recognition...
I think I have pictures here.
Let me just see. There it is.
The nomination highlighted Bethany's recognition that a strong school
library is a necessity, not a luxury, particularly for
students who face challenges outside of school.
Further, she understands that representation matters, and the school
library must reflect and honor all students' identities and
experiences. The school's inclusion of the first
permanent I'm
Your Neighbor welcoming library collection is a tangible
manifestation of this work. Bethany's impact extends
across the state through her volunteer work on the working
group on the status of school libraries and public libraries in Maine,
which examines the current state and future needs of school and public
libraries across Maine. The school community celebrated the
honor with a surprise assembly themed around her love of
birds. That's why you see Bethany sitting here
holding a big white goose, I believe is what it is.
And the kids ended up celebrating by wearing
handmade bird masks,
a school-wide bird-themed song, and a
specialty craft nest thrown in her
honor.
So congratulations to Bethany.
Is Bethany here tonight?
I am not Bethany Conley. She is unfortunately at home watching
as she is ill tonight, but I am sure was pleased to accept the honor.
Well, congratulations, Bethany.
This has made her feel a little bit
better tonight.
So next, we have the recognition of the championship boys indoor
SPHS track team, and I'm going to invite first,
Coach Cahill, if he wants to come forward and give any
introduction to what we're about to do or anything you would like to
say.
Thank you, Chairperson DeAngelis.
We, this year,
had a magical season
with the track and field team because we were just so cohesive,
supportive, and enthusiastic all year long.
We achieved our potential with an incredible state championship meet, and
it was one of the most enjoyable and rewarding seasons of my
coaching career. And of course, the championship made it that much more
magical because it was with such a wonderful
team. And that cohesion, support,
enthusiasm,
definitely is not just limited to the team.
South Portland, like many communities in Maine,
experienced a number of
adversities this year, and it extended
through parents,
obviously the entire coaching staff, community,
and everybody from the bus drivers,
right up through teachers and administrators,
and the incredible coaching staff that we have.
So again, it's really a magical season,
and that cohesion, support, and enthusiasm that we had the
entire year
is going to really benefit this community, and these
guys will definitely be leaders in the future.
Thank you very much, Coach Cahill.
Superintendent Entwistle and I are going to go down to the podium, and we're going
to call each one of you up,
and Coach Cahill is going to tell us who's not here.
So we're going to pass that certificate to him.
But we have a certificate for each one of you, and
we will give you... When we're done, we're going to have you come up
on the dais here and kind of scrouge in together in
two rows so we can get a picture of you all and
give you our congratulations at that point, okay? All right, great.
If you stand over here, you'll be able to see the names that are coming up.
Sure.
And I'll just flip them this way. Yes.
I'm not here.
Isaac Array.
Do I go next?
Yeah, you- Gabe Babineaux.
Yes.
Devin Berry.
Andrew Borelli.
Yes.
Amos Casimiro.
I want
to get two of these.
Yeah, I know.
Yes.
Bosai...
I got it.
Let's see if he does, okay? Didandike.
No.
No. No. No.
Yes.
Colin Hulsey.
Getting it right.
Yeah. Gill Ingram.
No.
I struggle.
That's what I was
saying.
Yes.
George Jenkins.
Oliver Jenkins.
Yes.
Joshua Kapita.
Noah Kay.
Lamin Kelidande.
This is your brothers?
Lamed.
Laislamu.
Yes.
Remy Khiala.
Folson Lemer.
Let me catch up here.
Excuse me.
Jared LaRose.
Yes.
Michael Lawler.
TheoMalley.
Yes.
Giovanni Meworkin.
Ambrosio Maputo.
Yes.
Asta Mukala.
Padu Mukala.
Yes.
Ben Neves.
Anthony Nielsen.
Derek Nuna.
No.
Yes.
Caleb Ramsell.
Rex Risem.
Mike Riseman.
Sego Rogers.
Yes.
Gavin Sturgis.
Daniel
Chichente.
Coach David Cahill.
Coach Matt Toothaker.
Assistant Coach Max Ludwig.
Assistant Coach Jordan Hulse.
Assistant Coach Mary DeSanto.
Assistant Coach Kyle Hartford.
There we go.
Okay, so now we're going to figure out how to get you up here.
Thanks.
Please fix that. I don't think it's getting clipped. Let me just...
I don't think-- Uh.
Let me just take it this way.
I don't think we... Yeah.
Yep.
I mean, you know.
If you want a picture, just take a picture there.
That's a pretty cool picture.
Yeah, that is a good picture.
That's a really cool picture.
Yeah.
I don't need to be in it.
Yeah, I'm not.
Good job once again.
We could like sprinkle in.
I think we could totally fit in.
Rosemary, we could like just sprinkle in with them.
Okay. All right.
And Stephanie just stand up here.
All right. It's going to just be... I mean, there could be one set on the floor.
Okay.
Yes.
Don't get hurt.
Knees up. Gotta get in tight. Stand in the back
there or sit.
You're
definitely going to have to get out of here.
We can have people sit here and people stand.
Look at that great picture.
They're doing things now.
Oh, that's a good idea.
I don't mind that. It's just like this one.
You found it? Can you guys maybe come around and stand with me?
Yeah.
I could
scare
people.
The only thing, it's just the height though. I think it's good.
Let's
get more close to the two.
No, you're good. We're going to go around.
That's okay. It's good.
Squeeze in as much as you can.
Okay,
I got it. It's them, not me. What did I do? Nothing.
That's okay.
It's okay.
It's good.
Thank you. I know. It's absolutely unbelievable.
They're like besties. I mean, they are.
You guys want to come around the side?
Might be able to squeeze you
in.
It's
very
awkward.
Do it slight.
Push in that way a
little
bit.
Go
ahead.
Oh, yeah.
Smile.
I got it? Okay.
Thank
you. Thank
you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
All
right.
Thank you. We did
it.
Everything is wonderful.
Thank you,
coach.
You know, Henry made it to the Northeast Finals for discus for
Bowdoin.
What is it?
My boyfriend.
Oh, because you mean it so much. It's okay.
We going to have just one more round of applause for these young men.
Absolutely. We have Athletic Director Livingston wants
to say something, so I'm going to let you speak.
If you guys want to hold for one second because-
Hang on
... Mr. Livingston is going to say something. Go ahead.
Yeah.
I just wanted to offer my congratulations again to the team and the coaches.
As you heard, Coach Cahill, just a wonderful group
of young men and their leaders as coaches.
I also just wanted to share that
I hear so often the comments made about our coaching staff
as I'm at meets and whatnot, and I wanted to share tonight
that Coach Cahill was also named the "Portland Press Herald" Coach of
the Year. So congratulations to him.
Thank you very much, Mr. Livingston.
And thank you again. Thank you, David.
Next on our agenda is the update for the FY
26-27 budget development. All right. We love that.
I'd like to call Abigail Ketchen.
Okay.
Can I make this smaller?
Pardon. Thank you.
Okay. Good evening. I'm Abigail Ketchen, Director of Finance,
and I'm going to give just a brief budget update and offer some information
as you all have your discussions.
Next slide.
Okay.
Oh, that
looks okay there, but not over there.
So there are many ways to look at a budget.
Oh, can you hear? Okay. Yeah. There's many ways to look at a budget.
The most common way that we present our budget in our
discussions,
the way the budget sort of gets presented to taxpayers is
in cost centers. For example, cost center
number one is instruction, cost center number two is special
education.
And I've just been thinking about how it might be useful to
sort of see another sorting of our budget, and that is by
location.
So what you're looking at is kind of a before and after
version of our budget, with instead of sorting by cost centers, I'm
sorting by where the activity is taking place, so
by location.
So if you look at the very top line, I'm highlighting capacity of the
building, specifically for the elementary schools.
And then in the light gray, what you can see is our
full, the all-in budget. So the way the budget
development process works, we start with a roll forward, just
what does it cost to maintain what we think we have right now, and
then we add on new costs, capital expenses,
whatever else we think we might need.
Departments have their requests.
We enter in other increases that are needed, and
that yields the all-in full budget amount.
And then underneath that, you can see where things are at
right now, but this time it's sorted by location.
A little bit of background in how
something like this gets generated.
So every
transaction has an account string,
and different pieces of the account string mean different things.
So let's say if a teacher's working at Brown, part of the
account string means education, part of the account string means school fund.
There's a piece that means teacher.
There's a piece that means Brown Elementary School.
So
a
swath of charges, it's very clear where they belong in
terms of location. But then we have other cost centers
that just feel a little different,
and that's specifically facilities, transportation.
So some of those costs,
it's not clear to see just where they belong by location.
So I went through all of those different types of charges and assigned a
location. For some charges, it makes sense to,
say, divide by number of schools. For other types of charges, it would be
prorated by a rough count of
enrollment.
And then this is where things have landed, just looking
retroactively
in a location sorting.
And part of the reason why I wanted to go back, look at
location, do a reanalysis of that part,
was because I think there's some slight misunderstanding about
what it cost and what the reductions actually meant
with a school closure.
There was a
meeting a few sessions ago where I pointed out how I
reduced about 400,000 or so from the facilities
piece
to account for facilities having one less building.
And I think that may have led to some confusion, thinking that, "Oh, that's what
it costs to keep that open." And so
looking back at the location-based, if we
accounted for it in this way, I think we can see that
it's not quite 400,000.
The school, I would
assign it about 5.7 million in our all-in budget.
Now, as we've moved from the all-in budget to
revising, as we've gone along the way, there's just
a small amount there, and that's for some minimum utilities to keep the
school, keep the electricity on to a small degree
so the pipes don't burst, that sort of thing.
And then you'll see the other schools, they actually have bumps up slightly to
account for that. But on the whole, for the elementary school, it's more like a $4
million or so impact on as part of our whole
budget.
So I wanted to offer that. I hope it's helpful.
If there are questions on it later, I'm happy to talk more about it.
But there you have that.
Next slide.And then as you're
all thinking about what you might ask the city,
things like tax increase, I just wanted to offer a
couple of examples of what the increase would mean in terms of dollars.
So if you were to increase, for example, the ask to taxpayers by a half a
percentage, that would add about 255,000.
If you were to bump it up to 7%, that would add about
540,000.
For context, that's four to five teachers,
in terms of what that would mean.
And then I am looking at FY28
pretty carefully. I have my own mock-up of how I'm thinking
the year might shake out. With that said, there
are
a long list of unknowns still at this point.
But I think that I've analyzed enough that I can say
that we will have to do some careful planning ahead
if we want to remain under 6% the following
year.
Okay, so I just wanted to offer that as part of your discussions.
Thank you.
Any questions? Are there any questions for Ms. Ketchen?
Yes.
Ms. Richardson. Member Richardson.
Thank you for that. That was really helpful to look at it that way,
the prior slide.
Mm-hmm.
When you said
overall $4 million impact-
Mm-hmm
... with the closure, you mean we basically took $4
million out of our budget by closing a school?
Yeah, I would say closing a school
is about half of the full reductions that we've made.
It accounts for about half of it, if you add up all the elementary lines before and
after.
Yep.
Mm-hmm.
And the caution for careful planning for next year.
Could you be a little bit more specific?
I have a long list of unknowns. I really do, and a lot of the
unknowns could create big swings.
The health insurance is a big swing, the EPS Essential
Services Report, that figure could make a big swing.
I feel like I know enough that it's not going to be like
this next year because of all the reductions that we've made.
I feel pretty confident about that, pending some of these big drivers.
Included on my list is worldwide events, right?
There are certainly big things that can-
Is what?
Included on my own list of things that could change is worldwide
events.
Oh, worldwide events.
Yeah. There's a list of things that can happen.
So I don't want to back myself into a corner
on this one, but I have my
own roll-forward budget, and I am looking very carefully, and I have a list
of factors that I'm going to be really reviewing and being
super cautious about and explaining along the way.
But I would say I know enough that
it-
Yep
... it won't be so bad, but we will have to really think about things.
Two questions.
Mm-hmm.
Have we received any update from the DOE on the
extra-- Okay, no. Extra 300K?
No.
No. Okay.
Second question is the EPS formula, so updates to that.
My understanding,
very preliminary understanding-
Mm-hmm
... was that
we will potentially benefit under that new model positively,
right? I know some towns might be impacted negatively by that, but there's
supposed to be... There was some
conclusion that that may be a beneficial new calculation for
us in term-- And when I say beneficial, I mean more dollars.
Do you have any insight into that?
That's my impression at this time.
Okay.
I haven't checked the report today.
I have not checked the EPS today.
Yes.
Yeah.
Do you know when we would know
what that number might look like?
For FY28 or-
Yeah
... FY27?
Well, FY27, I thought we knew the EPS.
Oh, the EPS report changes throughout the year.
So I guess, when do you think we might have a projection for
FY28 under the new calculation?
For FY-
The statute, it's February 1st, is when we-
Okay
... have to have our allocation.
Okay.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you.
Are you also-
If there's any other information or things you have along the way, I'll try to
calculate as fast as I can.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Any other questions before
Ms. Ketchen sits down?
Okay, thank you. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
So,
just continuing the-
Yeah, please
... the
report that I have is really enrollment.
And it's interesting.
We're
right about one kid short of where we were when
we started, actually. So it's been interesting,
watch this in graph form.
Thank you, Eleni, for suggesting it.
It's kind of
something interesting to watch each week.
And then, the last part of my report has to do with
resignations.
And we have received
resignations from Victoria Argies,
special ed teacher, Skillin. That's effective at the end of
August. Caitlin Field, grade one teacher, Dyer
Elementary, effective same time, and Beth
Kellogg, principal, Brown Elementary School, and that's effective at
the end of June.
We also put together a bit of a special education
update. There were a lot of questions.
And we have Kate Cox.
KateKat Cox.
Sorry. I'm tripping up on names. Kat Cox,
she's the office right next to me, and we chat all the time.
Anyway, Kat Cox, the Director of Instructional
Services. And there's a few
slides that we have and I'll turn it over to her.
Welcome, Kat.
Thank you. Of course, I just lost my
presentation. Hopefully, I can read it from here.
I was worried I wouldn't be able to read it. So good evening everybody.
I'm Kat Cox, and I'm the Director of Instructional Support for South Portland.
I know there's been a couple of questions that have lingered from the budget
process, so I thought I would put some slides together to give some clarity to some
of the topics that we've talked about.
So the first thing is really to talk about OTs and the model
of the embedded OTs.
I think it probably makes sense for those that aren't school folk to at least
explain that occupational therapy in elementary schools
is really focused around fine motor skills, adaptive
equipment that kids may need. It could be as simple as a stool under their desk,
so their feet are grounded. It could be a slant board, so those kind of
things. They also work on activities of daily living
skills and self-care skills, among other things, but those are some
of the key ones.
So the embedded OT model that was created, was created right
around COVID on the flip side of sort of coming
back to school. We made a lot of efforts to hire,
and we still felt like we were running short.
And so it was my brainstorm to trade in two ed techs for an
OT to embed because we really needed more staff
in those classrooms.
And so I think we had one turnover of an OT in that
time, but it has worked pretty well.
They have been good matches in that classroom.
That model is only used in two of our life skills
classrooms out of six in the district.
And just for clarity, in case people are wondering what's the sixth, we have two
classrooms at Dyer School. We have one in every other school.
Just realizing the one at Small has changed from year to year, depending
on the needs of kids. So just in case people ask that question.
So the State of Maine sets the rule around
how high a caseload can be for an occupational therapist at
50. Now, I'm not recommending 50. I'm sure
Rosemary probably remembers speech paths are also 50, and that's really
not doable.
So it's just important to know as a guide that we are not supposed to
go over that number.
So
there are numbers within the state limits, but certainly not
something I would advocate for, just for clarity.
So now I move to next year in the budget.
So what we're really doing is we are going back to pre-COVID and
going back to the model that is followed in all the other buildings throughout the
district.
So OT services are provided either direct or consultative,
and some kids get both.
It does not rule out the possibility of doing some embedded
services in specific situations, but I leave that to the OTs
to decide. It may be appropriate to push into a classroom for something,
but the pull-out model is often used as well in elementary
schools.
So one of the issues that got raised when people raised concerns about the
embedded OTs was around dysregulation of students and really
feeling like the OT played a heavy role in that.
So OTs can still play a role in that through consultation and service.
But one of the things I wanted to make sure I highlighted in the new budget is that
each elementary school will have a half of BCBA for special
education students and half of an instructional strategist.
Both of those positions can be pretty key in supporting these classrooms.
So I just want to make sure I highlighted that.
So the change now would leave us with 3.8
OTs in the district. So one of our OTs
works four out of five days.
So what the state says that they should be able to carry is
190 kids. Now, by no means, I don't want anybody
quoting me, I am not advocating for them to have that many kids,
but the number that is projected for us, including incoming CDS kids,
is 138 kids in the district. Now, those
IEPs are not all completed yet, so some of those numbers can certainly
change. And one of the factors of CDS is that it's
rolling, constant enrollment. So we will continue to get
kids that either move in or get identified, or they move into the
district. So that number keeps changing right up until the first day of
school.
So the State of Maine regulations define the OT case log, and
I explained that to you as 50. The OT ratio for us would be
1 to 36. And 36 is a big number, but
one of the things I just want to highlight is that OTs do not carry case
management responsibilities, which our speech paths do, as well as
our special education teachers. And there's a long list
of what our case managers do, but it is the primary contact for
parents when they need to find out information about their student's
program, setting up meetings, issues that come up.
So it is quite a bit of work. So that definitely is a time
save.
But it is important to know that OTs do have evaluation
responsibilities. They have assessment responsibilities.
And just to tell the difference between those two things, assessment is not
something you need parental permission for.
We are constantly assessing our students about the progress on their goals, where
evaluation really is a more formal process that we need parent consent
to make determinations of whether they require OT services or
they don't.
Any questions about OT so far?
Any
questions?
Sure, Member Smith.
Can you go back to that previous slide?
Absolutely.
Just a quick question about the change.
So it says now that under the FY27,
each elementary school will have half-time BCBA-
Yeah
... and each will have a half-time instructional strategist.
Are those completely new positions in those, or is
that-
One of the instructional strategists is a new position, and the BCBAs
are not new to the district.
Okay.
But when we first started having strategists, one strategist was covering four
elementary schools. So it is a much richer model to
have two buildings per person.
Okay, and the half-time BCBA,
how many does each elementary school have right now?
Right now they have... Oh, let me just calculate that.
I have one person who is in Skillman School
as a full-time person, half regular, half special ed, so basically half
of a person out of mine.
Yeah.
And then I have a person that was in...
Hold on. Let me see if I get this right.
She was reduced, and so she is not covering Dyer anymore because she was
doing four buildings, and that was too much.
So the BCBA from the high school has been coming down to help Dyer School.
Okay.
Yeah, that's all I have.
Thank you. Question, Member Richardson.
Can you go back to that other slide, please?
But you had a behavior strategist, right?
My understanding is that those were all called behavior strategists.
Some just have a BCBA certification, right?
All of the ones in special education now are all BCBAs.
Right.
And the strategist role was not supporting special ed, correct?
The
regular ed behavior strategist? Correct.
Yeah. And I know I've asked this of
Joe, and I'd love to hear-
Sure
... your answer too, but
my concern is we had
this embedded model. Sounds like it worked really well.
We
continue to have issues staffing these classrooms from an ed tech
perspective. So I'm concerned that
we're going to continue to see those vacancies, whereas we
haven't had that turnover from the OT.
So can you just help me get more comfortable with-
Absolutely. In fact, the next two slides are about ed techs, so
I think that might help answer that question.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Next one.
There you go. So how do we assign ed techs in the first place throughout the
district? So we identify the students.
This is a pretty key time of year because we're doing CDS transition
meetings. Currently, we are transitioning 83 students from child
development services into special education.
So we go through that process. We determine the needs that we have currently
with all of our other students, and then we look at the whole K to
12 ed tech pool. So it isn't as though all the ed techs that were at
Dyer are all the ones that will be there next year, or all the ones that were the
middle school are the ones that will be there. It's always based on student need.
So those positions do get moved sometimes for
student need.
Okay. So then the last piece is once we combine all of
those things, we look at the total pool and decide where placements need to be, and
that generally happens right as school is letting out because we have
CDS meetings right until the end of the year.
So I'll go through a couple of bullet points down below.
So IEP team meetings in the district have already been completed.
Of course, annuals are always going on, so those numbers are always
fluctuating, and we keep on top of them
while we're doing the CDS transition planning.
The other key piece is that we introduced two ed tech
positions back into the budget, and thank you for that.
So that is a little bit of a relief. And the other piece is we no longer have ed
tech ones. We are only doing twos and threes, which afford us more
flexibility.
Go ahead.
So some of the challenges I want to outline
with the ed tech situation to begin with, right?
So ed tech hiring has been consistently difficult, not just here, but throughout
the state. I hear it from directors all the time.
High needs
for trained personnel, particularly ed techs two and three with behavior or special
ed experience. That continues to be a challenge.
Ongoing shortages mean principals frequently reassign
staff and can disrupt student routines.
Our principals are masters at this, but they are always
just handling the next thing, right?
They just always know how to use their staff effectively.
And then addressing safety concerns for classrooms that are short-staffed.
So the actions that I would like to take is, first, I'd
like to explore the consideration for
referral for ed techs. I know we did this with
transportation drivers quite a while ago.
Andy, do you recall what year it was?
Four years ago.
Four years ago. And so I would just like to explore that and
talk with Abigail about what that cost would be.
The next one is full use of Indeed or ZipRecruiter or
those kind of platforms. And why this one is important is
Indeed, back in the COVID days, used to give you a
function where you could invite people to apply.
That is not part of the basic program anymore, but I will
tell you the only way I was able to find ed techs during the COVID
time was I would spend evenings inviting 30 to 40 people a
night to apply, and I would get six to eight applications.
And I just kept doing it night after night after night, and we were able to get
pretty close, but obviously the OT piece helped
finish that for us a little bit.
The other thing I am exploring is outside
agency partnerships for
BHP-credentialed staffAnd I will tell you, I've
not been a fan of this in the past, largely because when you
have those folks come into your school, you do not supervise them.
The outside agency supervises them.
So for many years, I've had conversations with previous superintendents about
being worried about that.
However, there are a couple of agencies that we have used for other
things that are quite reputable. I feel really good
about the services they provide. I don't want to announce who they are, but
I feel like they would be people I would
absolutely consider doing this partnership with, because I really trust the
services they provide and the BCBAs that they employ.
So, that is something I would like to pursue and see if that would be
helpful. Again, I mentioned the
prioritizing ed tech twos and threes for hire.
Gives us more flexibility. The ones need a pretty high
amount of supervision, so that gets a little bit hard.
And then the last is the ongoing training, which is an ongoing conversation
for us right now about how do we provide enough training, not just to
incoming people, but when somebody leaves in the middle of the year, how do we make
sure there's training available that can be done on the fly and not
necessarily need a whole group or a room full of people, but something
perhaps online to be able to do that.
Any questions about the ed tech?
Questions.
Just-
Member-
Sure.
BHP credentialed. What's BHP?
It's a behavioral health practitioner.
So really the biggest difference between an ed tech...
And I would argue we have some extraordinary ed techs in this district that are
not BHPs, so I don't necessarily think they're the end-all be-all.
Okay.
It really is the quality of the person in doing the job.
But they do receive 40 hours worth of training on top of any
education that they have.
Member Risch.
If you have a lot of turnover, is there any way we could do an exit interview and
see why they're leaving? Do we collect that data?
Certainly be willing to talk to HR about that.
Okay. It'd just be nice just to build some sort of-
Sure. And sometimes our ed techs leave for good reason, too.
I know we had a resignation not that long ago.
Somebody was going on to be a teacher.
And that, while it's horrible when we lose staff, we certainly want to celebrate
when people are moving-
Definitely
... in a better direction.
Thank you.
Other questions?
Member Richardson.
So,
in terms of the, I think it was the previous slide that kind of shows the life
cycle of how you-
Sure.
Yeah. So is it fair to say that we really don't know how many
special ed techs we need, like for the
next year? Because-
It's not completely solidified yet, no.
Because it's based on the number of IEPs.
Yes.
Is there, uh-
And the needs in each IEP.
Yeah. So
how many special ed techs do we have right now in the-
Oh, that's great. I knew you were going to ask me that question.
I wish I had grabbed the number.
Yeah.
I don't know. You know what? I will get you that number and send it to you.
That would be-
Because we have some in local budget, and we have some in the federal local
entitlement budget.
But I heard 100. It sounds like it's a lot.
Yeah. It is a lot.
Okay. So,
each IEP, let's say each child belongs
to an IEP.
Each IEP depends on whether or not that's a full
special ed tech.
Mm-hmm.
Like .5.
Yes.
Like all that, and you're basically... Yeah.
Exactly. And all of our kids from CDS that have a-
Right. Sure.
Yeah.
Right.
Any of our kids from CDS currently that have a relative high
need, meaning a higher staff ratio through CDS, we actually
send somebody to go observe. So I went and saw somebody last week.
We have a couple of our other folks going out, so we have a little bit more
information.
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
Mm-hmm. You're welcome.
Other questions?
One more. Oh, go ahead.
Rosemary, did you say you had a question?
No, I was asking if anybody-
Oh, okay
... had any more questions.
And the last thing I just wanted to show, just because restraint and seclusion is
just, again, we should never make decisions based on
one source of data. We certainly learn that in special education,
but it is in just a snapshot of our restraint and seclusion data
last year and this year, but for a set period of time, because we, of course, don't
know the full amount for this year.
So during the same period of time, the blue bar is from last year,
and the red bars are from this year, and that is the total amount of
incidences.
Any questions about that?
Any other questions?
Member Richardson.
And in both the blue and the red, you had the OT-embedded model, right?
It's not-
Only in a dire school, and it's Gillan school.
Okay. So we can't know what the
impact of the loss of the OT model really is.
Well, not fully, just because there's so many variables-
Yeah
... attached to that.
But in terms of like this, it doesn't matter.
Yes.
They were in the... Yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
You're welcome. Anything else?
Any other questions?
I only wanted to say that,
when I worked as a speech and language pathologist, I thought the
district did
an excellent job with trying to keep our caseloads...
They were far lower than 50,
closer to 35, between 30 and 35. And even
though at that time, I covered multiple buildings, and there's
now less of that,
I really applaud the district on managing
caseload sizes for us, and I think we
really pay attention to that and pay attention to the needs of students.
We really do try to do that, and I never look at that through the lens
of the amount of people they have, also the service hours they have.
So that's another data point that we pay attention to.
Yes. Thank youAny other questions?
Okay, seeing none. Thank you.
Thank you.
Now, do you have anything else, Superintendent Entwistle?
No. Can we move to public comment?
Please.
I had a question about the resignations.
Are those
resignations that
we knew about?
So will we be looking to the recall list to-- Great.
Thank you.
Well, for the teacher, right? Not for the
principal. The two classroom teachers. Okay, cool. Thanks.
So we are up to the first public comment, and
I
know that Superintendent Entwistle
requested that there be a motion to limit public
debate again, and I don't know if anybody has a motion to do that or not.
Do we? I don't know. Do we need it?
Yeah. I'm just asking.
I don't think so.
No. No.
Speaker 75.
And the other thing I would say is, I just want to remind people because some
people came in late,
that I did read in the beginning that there has been a lot
of feedback from parents, and I want people to know we're listening, and
we will have an action item on the agenda on April 29th
to halt the movement forward on
reconfiguration at this time with a movement
to the fall of 2027.
And
there's strong support on this board to delay this action, and the decision
to do it on April 29th is for two primary reasons: to
allow for sufficient public notice and to afford
time to write the action item correctly.
But it's clear that this board supports this delay, and we appreciate
your expression of concerns.
So with public comment,
the board's public comment time is an opportunity for the board to listen
to opinions of the public that relate to school and education matters on or
off this evening's agenda. The board is here to listen.
Anyone wishing to speak will be asked to proceed to the microphone and state
your name and the city or town where you reside.
Questions will be attempted to be reported by the
superintendent and/or the chair with some help from other people up
here, which I appreciate, and will be answered at the end of public comment to
the extent possible. So if answers are not
available or if we miss your questions,
we'll get them on the recording following the meeting, and someone will
be assigned to reply to you as soon as the answer is available.
You'll be given three minutes to speak.
We would ask that there be no interaction between the public and board members.
Additionally, no clapping, booing, or other interruptive behavior.
And as a reminder, school board meetings are broadcast live and
recorded and posted on the city's website.
So please consider the impact of your comments. So Sarah.
Hello. Sam Merrill in Sawyer Street, South Portland.
I wanted to talk briefly about a time crunch and
sort of a breaking point. And this comment is
relevant. It's different now because of the
anticipated motion that was mentioned, which I
appreciate, but I think it may still play into that
process where it's about how
what was most concerning to me among the things, one of the concerning things
about the reorganization
plan was about thinking about the mornings and getting kids to school.
And say a mom who had a kid in first, third, and fifth grade who might suddenly
have to get kids to three different schools.
That was
something I was thinking about. I have four kids.
And the mornings, there's always
this challenge getting out the door, and there's a break
point at which it doesn't work anymore, and if you've got so many transitions.
And of course, the response is, "Well, that's what the buses are for,"
right? They're going to get people to the different places.
But at the same time,
there's still more
coordination and transitioning and getting two different points that's involved in
all of that, and it can reach a break point.
And the reason I'm here is because I rolled up as a
person in the
disabled community, where one thing that people don't think about a whole
lot
is that transitions take
people in wheelchairs a lot longer,
so that if you're near that break point because of having to do three schools or
three buses, in and out of the car, in and out of bus, et cetera, in a morning when
you got a lot going on, and that's near your break point for maybe I can't get to
work today because it's just too much. I can't fit it all in.
Well, think about that.
When I go to the store, just the time to transition in and
out of a vehicle
can be as much as most people take to go into the store and do their groceries and
get home. It takes a lot of time to transition.
So that could push the break point for the disabled community.
That's my point.
It might help in the reorganization process because
if you're going to take time to think about it properly, well, take that
into account.
Thank you, Sam.
Sam also serves on the Bicycle Pedestrian Committee, and he is a great
reminder to us frequently about sort of looking
at things through a different lens. So I always appreciate that. So thank you, Sam.
Sarah.
Hi. Sarah Gay. This is the best voice I've got. I'll do my best.
Parent, educator, president of the South Portland Teachers Association,
voter, taxpayer.
So I'm really grateful that we can listen to comments like these, and now
that is something we can consider proactively, not
reactively.That's huge. I would
be horrified to think of consideration for
every member of our community's needs not being fulfilled because we didn't
have the opportunity to actually explore every piece.
So, thank you for listening to the many voices in our community who have called for
the opportunity to have a thorough and appropriate process.
At the back of the room by the board meeting agendas, I've left some printed
copies of some takeaways from a survey that our
association sent to our members about a week and a half ago,
and now we have those results compiled and shared on our
website. I've shared them with the board and district leaders.
There's a QR code you can grab if you'd like to look at those full results on our
website. I'm going to share a few notable data points.
It's a lot less than I was going to share an hour ago, which I, from a voice
perspective, appreciate.
But some of this is still very significant.
So 85.6% of our surveyed members,
who
for data verification purposes, we had 187
participants. Our unit represents,
it is 283 out of the
350 members of our bargaining unit, so this was about 66%
participation from our members.
Notably, that 85.6% feel that
transparency has not been the
manner in which we have received information about cuts.
And I can attest as the president of the association that we
have not received sufficient information to justify all of these cuts.
75.4% of our members wanted the school board to increase the amount that
will be approved, or the school board to ask the city council to increase the
amount that will be approved for funding for next year.
Cool.
77.5% still do not approve of the budget, and I think a great deal
of those concerns come from the fact that there had been so many
uncertainties and so many unknowns.
They're still there, they're just in a different place now.
So in response to the budget, specifically separate from reconfiguration-
30 seconds, Sarah
... there's still an enormous amount that is going to need to be impact bargained,
and I just want to make sure that everyone in the community is aware that that is
going to be a lengthy process.
I'll use my last few seconds to just say that Kaylor needs some real love, you
guys, like really desperately. That community has been
just completely ripped to pieces, and
those staff members, those students, their families need to know where they are
going as soon as humanly possible.
We need to think about how we are going to transition them through the end of the
school year. It's not a small thing to close a school.
So please give them-
Three minutes, Sarah
... the care that we can. Thank you.
Thank you, Sarah.
Hi, my name is Aiden Ranahan. I'm a parent of a Brown School kindergartner.
I live on Stanley Street.
Well, certainly my comments are also very different.
I want to thank the board for considering pausing the timeline.
I think I've done a lot of outreach to really emphasize that I think
more space really gives this process more
time. One of the things I wanted to talk about, which I mentioned in the listening
session, was kindergartners and my kindergartner who's facing the
potential of three school transitions in three years.
I know that's also a huge
top of mind for the Kaylor families, and I really believe that there's a
solution here, and I don't know if it's phased approach.
I don't know if it's switching grades over time, but I think there can be a better
way, and time allows that to be a better way. So I really appreciate that.
As we move to the next phase of this conversation, I think I just want to emphasize
three things to the board.
First, I really think there's still work to do to make the case.
I genuinely believe with the conversations I've had in the community that people
want to do the right thing. People understand that there may be need gaps, but I
think people are really looking for more transparency and more data.
I think there's a belief that borders and configuration did a lot of this work, but
I want to emphasize that the elementary school population potentially turns over
25% every year with parents moving into middle school where they don't have
this focus on borders and configuration.
And so I think even though that process is only two or three years old, making the
case is important. And I was looking at Miss Fletcher's numbers, and
one of the things that struck me is if you just do some napkin math, the per pupil
spending for a small student is 38,000, I think, and
the per spending per a Skillman student is 28,000.
And I know
Director Fletcher will say, "Don't use those numbers," because there's a million
coding things, and I'm aware of that, but I think
that it just points to digging into the data really can point to some
of the areas of need, and I think it can help put together a plan that really
addresses some of those needs, and I think the community would respond well to
that. I also think doing more community engagement in the listening sessions have
been a great start, but I think, like I said,
my family, who's parents of a kindergartner facing more transitions, I think
there's pockets of needs there. And I think like I shared,
I was talking about this process at a birthday party, and so many of the parents
said, "I didn't realize this was happening, and I don't have time to engage on this
issue." So I think finding those pockets of needs and meeting them where they are
and having those engagement, I think can put more of people's issues in the
discussion set, right? Because I think that's what needs to happen, is community
engagement is to collect the issues, and some of them may be small and some of them
may be big, but they're not all going to be visible, especially in a forum like
this-
30 seconds left
... with a lot of yelling, frankly.
The last thing I'll say is transparency, right?
I think everybody feels that there will be trade-offs, and everybody knows there
will be trade-offs, and I fundamentally do not believe this community is afraid of
trade-offs. What the community is afraid of is trade-offs that are made
behind closed doors. And so frameworks, discussions, a
process, a committee, which I think is a great idea, I think those are the things
that address and assuage the fear of people who just want to make sure that they
have their voices heard and a seat at the table.
That's three minutes.
Thank you very much for reconsidering, and I look forward to working with everyone.
Thank you very much. Glenn.
Hello. Vladimir Korshin, parent of a kindergartner at Small School.
First of all, yes, like others, I want to thank you all very much for,
after a delay hearing our voices, that this
timeline was just too short, and that it was distracting
from more pressing issues like this massive budget overhaul,
a lot of teachers losing their jobs, and also a closure of a
school.
I think that I would like to see the effort that we put in to stopping
reconfiguration on the timeline, and again, I just want to emphasize that
not everyone in our movement was against reconfiguration.
It was about the timeline.
I think that whether or not reconfiguration is a good idea should be had on its own
merits when there's enough time to evaluate it fully.
I think the focus should be on Kaylor, as you mentioned, and specifically,
if it is still possible to keep that school open.
I feel like that has been almost,
I don't know what the word is, but maybe a defeatist attitude towards that concept,
and I understand that,
I guess, is it $4 million to keep it open approximately?
I would love to see
a voter initiative or a ballot measure to see if there
can be a funded--
If the city is willing to pay that for some number of
years in order to avoid an urgent and imminent closure.
I think that
even if that closure needs to happen or let's say, at a different school, there
should be enough time. It's extremely jarring to have to close the school
on the timeline that you guys have set up.
So, yeah, I will now be putting my effort behind that,
and I hope to understand what the
sort of costs will be there. Thank you.
Thank you, Vladimir.
Hi, my name is Alex Strube. I'm a parent in South Portland.
I just wanted to thank the board for listening
to our teachers and our families,
and a lot of the feedback that has been provided over the last few weeks since a
few decisions have been made. Again, to kind of echo what
Vlad had been saying, it's really about the process, and having a thoughtful
process has been so important to this community, and so I'm grateful for
that. A parent I was talking to had made a comment to me
saying,
"Well, what is our vision for schooling?" In this process, I've
heard,
like Member Smith, you mentioned we're trying to just reduce
impact, right? I can't remember the exact words you used, but there was something
around, let's just minimize the hurt.
And there is real hurt here, right?
Even with giving more timeline on decisions, and
so would love to, I'm just thinking maybe it's through the steering committee or
another forum, but just how are we thinking about what is
our vision for the children in this district?
There's a lot of impacts that have been made within our middle school of certain
programs that are being cut, different other teachers that are being cut and
shifted around, and so as we step back and have an opportunity to think,
what is the vision? What are we trying to create as an education system
here? Would love to see how the community can be involved in that, to be able to
weigh in and provide support and input for especially
different
courses like computer science and the arts.
I think they're deeply important, and we want to be able to vote on those the way
we vote on grass. Thank you.
Thank you, Alex. Mr. Baxter.
Ralph Baxter. I live in South Portland.
I came with a written thing that I intend to read, but I also want to
say congratulations. Part of my talk is going to be about boards
and how you operate, how I feel you operate.
And whether I agree with what you're proposing tonight on later in the month,
I applaud you
reaching out, finding common ground.
I think you've heard, and you've listened, and thank you for that.
I started with what is happening. I wrote down a few things.
Executive sessions to discuss roles of a board member in April.
A member resigns after that.
A police presence at our meetings.
A police report filed by a board member about being harassed.
Recall elections.
I'm troubled by that, and I don't understand how you got here
and why you're here, and I'm not here to criticize you.
I'm here to support you. I should let you know, and I didn't really want to say
this, but I was a former board member.
I understand exactly what you're going through, and I empathize with what you're
doing. With that,
I'd say I doubt this is what you signed up for originally.
If you were like me, you were sitting around the dining room table, and you said,
"I think I'd like to try that." And I'm glad I did.
I'd do it in a heartbeat, circumstances not allowing.
But you did do it, and you're here.
You want to make a difference. You want to give back to SP. Good for you.
Congratulations.
Do what's right. Now's the time. You have the toughest
job in city government.
I know. I can hear the people back there, and I say this for two
reasons. You're spending my money and this
community's money, but you're also watching out for our students.
Two big jobs. Nothing bigger, in my opinion.
It's time to stop sniping, and that's maybe a poor choice of words, but that's
mine,
and start problem-solving, which it feels like you're doing.
Realize I wrote this yesterday. So
any person worth their salt who is interested in becoming a superintendent
here is watching what's going on, and it is so
important that we show that we're not all in agreement,
but we're at least talking, and we're understanding each other and where we're
coming from.
Please set a new tone that is clear that we are a
successful school department. I'm so tired of reading about our failures.
We are full of success
30 seconds left.
Thank you. I always hope that when there is a problem, that
someone has a solution, they offer it. I offer two thoughts.
Have a facilitated workshop with an outside
facilitator for goal-setting and
finding. It works. I've been there. I've done it.
It does work.
The second is to take a collective breath, especially before tomorrow night,
and reorder while you are here. Maybe that's where you
start understanding your group goals.
That's three minutes.
Thank you very much. And lead us through united.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you so much,
Ralph.
Hello, my name is Amy. I am a parent at Kayler School.
And I don't take it lightly, the amount of relief that I feel in
this room, that people are grateful for this extra time, that they can
work on this, and everyone can have their concerns heard and have more
transparency in the process. I appreciate that.
I really do.
But Kayler, we are not allowed that. We are not afforded that luxury.
And it feels very unfair that we're asking the
school that has the highest amount of renters, the highest amount of free
lunch or discounted lunch,
the second highest of multilingual learners, and the second highest in children of
color to bear the brunt of this right now, and that we
have to make these adjustments. I
understand the concerns, but it just, on its face right now, feels profoundly
unfair.
And I don't think that's been taken that much in consideration, the Kayler kids,
in this whole process, in anything I've been reading.
We instantly were put in this whole process that just
started a couple of weeks ago. We were
thrown under the bus by another school to be the ones that close.
I've read really horrible comments about Kayler online and
what people kind of thought of it, and it was called by one person, the Petroleum
Oil Farm School.
These types of comments sound very
prejudiced towards Kayler, and it's been really a hurtful experience.
So again, I appreciate the relief here that other people are feeling,
but while you're
breathing that sigh of relief, please take into consideration that there are
160 kids that are not afforded that, and they
are arguably one of the most vulnerable set of children in
South Portland.
Amy, thank you so much.
Thank you.
Hi. I'm Mindy Allos, parent in the district,
and also grew up here in South Portland.
My mother graduated from South Portland as well.
This will be pretty short.
I know this is all really hard. Our community is really
fractured. I think losing staff and
closing a school is heartbreaking.
One thing we could all probably agree on in this room is the wish for an unlimited
school budget, but that's not realistic.
I discourage asking for more money from the city.
We're becoming unaffordable. If we want to just push people out and
only have privileged folk here, then sure, let's keep raising
taxes. I don't think that is the proper
solution, and nor do I think that's a smart financial
decision.
I understand that some people are just now becoming involved, but the
conversation around reconfiguring our elementary schools to address the
inequities across the district is not new,
nor is it secret.
I would challenge the request for more time because we've had time.
I volunteered on the Boundaries and Configuration Steering Committee for about 16
months, beginning in January 2023.
During that time, many of the same voices asked for more
time.
Time is clearly not the answer.
Change is hard, and it's also inevitable.
I was part of a really hopeful meeting yesterday with parents who want to move
forward and support the district through reconfiguration.
We were brainstorming ideas to support staff and all of our students,
ideas on how to bring our community together, because we are
one community.
Asking Kayler families and staff to change schools this year and then again next
year is incredibly unfair. I urge you to reconsider
this change of course, and base decisions on the needs of our entire
community.
Thanks.
Thank you, Mindy.
Hi.
My name is Chloe Bartlett. I'm a third grade teacher at Dyer.
And this is my third year in the district. Can you hear me? Okay.
Reconfiguration is a major life-changing shift for students, staff, and the
community, and we all felt the power and weight of this decision.
So thank you for pausing the process.
I love South Portland. I love my community. I love teaching.
I love my students.
But I felt
it is very important to share that my heart was broken so many times this year.
Actually, it's just since maybe February.
As so many of us have been feeling, on the ground in the
schools, we feel a real loss of our colleagues and soon a
whole entire school.
I'm shaking. I'm so sad and scared to be up here.
But next March,
are we going to be going through another year of fear of being cut?
Are we going to go through another year
of not knowing? How are you going to ensure that the
trauma, stress, and loss that we felt through the communities aren't
repeated a third time in a row?
Again, it's my third year here. I love it and I'm
scared.
You halted the process, but the effects are still lasting.
So thank you for your time. I appreciate it.
Thank you very much, Ms. Bartlett.
If there are no other
public comment,
are public comments closed?
I think there was just one question,
and it might be more to you,
Abigail, but it was from this last speaker who
just spoke about what-- And Member Richardson
asked this as well. If you can just speak to sort of
what our upcoming year looks like
budgetary-wise.
And what this person just asked, Ms.
Bartlett, was
are we going to be going through another year of losses, and
how is that going to look?
All right, just give me one second.
No, take your time.
Abigail, do you want me to go back to that slide that we had before,
or?
Oh, no. No, I don't need it.
Okay. So our original just roll-forward budget, and
as a reminder, when we first roll forward, that's step one,
okay? And then we add on whatever other needs have
emerged, like other capital projects.
There
are missing items in an initial roll forward.
There are many assumptions in my initial roll forward, okay?
Including all staff stay in their
current position, they go to
their
next step in their contracts. If health
insurance is the exact same rate, that same 5.14,
which is not true, right? It's going to be something different
for sure.
If the payroll taxes are all the same,
mostly.
If electricity and natural gas, I added 15%, which is kind
of reasonable. There's a few things I escalated at
10%, and then everything else escalated around 5%,
which sort of weights the budget around that 5% mark, right?
And again, it's not possible to include everything at
this point, right? We haven't even started formally on the next year's budget.
So yeah, stipends, summer school tuition, maintenance projects, other
things, I escalated around 5%. If I assume
the city property valuation is the exact same,
probably not, right? That changes.
The same EPS,
probably not. It changes. The same TIF, probably not.
It definitely changes. And then on the revenue side, if
let's say 3% more on the other non-local tax revenue.
And keep in mind that what my initial roll forward does not include
is FY26 actuals because the year hasn't ended, and that's a
key piece of my analysis. So when I was thinking through
this year's, it's a key point of the analysis to know what the increase was
from the current fiscal year to the prior fiscal year in relation to the increases
in several fiscal years prior. So that is not in
existence yet.
There'll be a litany of sick retirement payouts.
Those would be due around November 1st of FY27,
and then we'd include that in FY28, so that's not there.
Remaining debt service analysis isn't there.
I did include the extra principal and interest payment.
But if we had concluded any other old debt, that's not included in my
analysis at this time.
And then we'll also be negotiating a new SEA contract,
right? So that a roll forward budget would not include however that
shakes out. And just keeping in mind, there's key
drivers that can wildly swing
how things shake out, the city valuation, health insurance, EPS,
unexpected capital needs, unexpected revenue, large grant funding
reductions, and worldwide events.
So if all that
shakes out in the way that
it could, but again, there's so many assumptions you can't really
know. But that puts us a touch over 6%,
and there'd be some light attrition that could do the job.
But again, there's so much that is unknown that I'm not predicting something like
this next year. But again, I wouldn't put ourselves in a
box on calling it at this point.
But I'm calculating things like this all the time because I think about this a
lot, and it's my personal agenda to go from one fiscal year
to another without layoffs and without strife.
And I'm trying to do everything I can on my end
to try to help enable decisions that will allow for that to happen.
But at this time, again, even with all I've said, there's too many unknowns.
Thank you. Appreciate that. Thank you.
That was a long rant. Thank you.
No, that's okay. That's all right.
Okay.
I think there was one other-
Oh, I'm sorry. Go ahead.
Do you mind?
No, go ahead, please.
Is it still possible to keep Kaylor open?
Oh.
Which I think you showed a little bit numbers-wise tonight.
Yeah.
I know.
I really don't think so. I'm very sorry.
If I thought there was a real path there financially, I would
love to see that be true.
I don't think that's the financial path forward.
And again, it's a community decision, right? The voters vote.
Well, it's also a leadership decision, but
I can't recommend that move financially.
Thank you.
Thank you, Abigail.
And did anybody find any other questions?
I didn't hear any others. It's the first time.
No.
Thank you.
We are at
report of committee, and so first is the finance
committee, Ms. Holman.
And Abigail has volunteered to-
She's back
... commandeer that in a great way.
Go, Abigail.
Okay. Hello again.
Okay, so now we're back in our current fiscal year,
FY26.
At this point in the year, we were about three quarters of the way through the
year. About 95% of our funds are either
expended or otherwise encumbered.
And again, encumbrance
means that we have placed a
numerical hold on an account. So let's say
you're going to have five more paychecks this year.
I'm placing a hold for five more of your paychecks.
That would be what an encumbrance is in that case, or if you
have an open PO for a
charge that you're going to have multiple invoices, those future invoices have a
numerical hold on the account.
So that's why it does make sense that there would be
noticeably more encumbered than the
percentage of year that has passed.
We do have an increase in expenses or estimates compared to the last
month's report. I think there's been
some noticeable uptick in some spending, facilities and
transportation in particular. There's been just required repairs that have
had to happen. And again, per our spending freeze, if it's essential for
safety, if it's required,
then we move forward.
Nutrition had a small uptick in their expected
and anticipated deficit.
Stipends are up, special ed is up primarily because we
finally made that payment that is related to
one of our repeat audit findings. So to
recap that one,
in our current FY25 audit, there was a repeat audit finding
related to an invoice early
January. It was like a
January to March invoice in the calendar year 2023.
So we had
a problem with that FY23 that was found in
FY24. We were supposed to pay it back in FY25.
We didn't, but now we have,
so that accounts for that uptick there.
But the good news is at least it's completed now.
And let's see. Some slight increase in telephone, other
tech costs.
And then I've noticed just a continued uptick in
spending
the first half of April that I think will inform the next report.
I'm obviously looking closely, and I'll
let you know at the end of the next month.
We've had a little bit of increase in revenue, specifically MaineCare.
And then I reduced the withholding account imbalance.
However, we have a real in-depth reconciliation
that we need to perform, and that is on our list and in part
of what we're working on. So overall, we have an updated potential range of
around 80K to 1.1 deficit.
There are things upcoming. We have a payroll software
for our payroll encumbrances that we're working on getting set up.
It's scheduled for the end of April.
So I'm looking forward to seeing
that get set up properly, and we'll see whether we can get
something set up for the rest of this fiscal year.
And if not, then certainly for FY27.
Accruals are coming up, withholding adjustments, and time beyond contract.
That's another piece that we're still working on figuring out,
and just that remains an unknown for our budget.
But we'll know more hopefully as soon as possible.
And then just as a reminder of things that will hit after the fiscal year,
electricity, final invoices. We'll also close things out and we'll have
our own year-end financial review, and adjustments will be made as we look back
through the year.
And of course, in the meantime, we're looking for any other ways we can save money.
And then beyond this report, we are
embarking on a pretty in-depth reconciliation project.
That was another one of our audit findings.
Benefits accounts, withholding accounts, the interplay between those two types of
accounts
is something that's been unreconciled for years.
And we've been having a heavy focus lately on
January through March health and dental bills, matching them up to
enrollments and real charges and the interplay between that
and the withholding accounts and then what's paid out.
And then we are also doing a pretty decent review so far
of the FY26 grants receivables. That was another audit
finding, so we're working through those grant by grant, month by month.
And then another thing that's upcoming is our paid family medical
leave program. We had, I think, a pretty
good meeting with SYMETRA this morning.
We had a lot of questions. I think we got some answers, and we'll
be
working between leadership and the union reps on sharing what
we're able to find out so far,
and then asking more questions as we go along.
But that is effective May 1st, so we are
very much pressed on that, and we want to be able to deliver
information as soon as possible
and also work things out with the unions.
Questions?
I don't think so. Oh, yes. Go ahead.
Hi.
One thing that you and I talked about today that I do just want to say
publicly is that the report that you have been
I forget what it's called. The
cost center breakdown with the scenarios-
Mm-hmm
... that you're providing to the financial committee every month
has very clearly in yellow, that I've kind of missed,
that it does not include possible additional expenses for time above
15 hours per new SPTA contract, further analysis needed.
Mm-hmm.
So
there is
an unidentified amount that's going to hit FY26
budget-
Mm-hmm
... and we don't know what it is.
That's correct.
Do we-
Correct. Yeah.
Do we think we will know that the next time we meet as a finance
committee?
Hmm.
In a-
Mm-hmm.
Johanna Prince, assistant superintendent.
So, over the course of the year, we have been working with the
SPTA on the process for how that time is
paid. Just at the end of last week, I was able to roll out phase one
of that to them and have asked for their submissions
between when the contract was ratified and current,
hopefully getting those in as soon as possible to ensure that those
folks are paid. I think that will be a very useful
way for us to then have a better estimate, so certainly by the time we
meet in a month, we would be able to have more.
And then on top of that, what I can share is that we are working,
excuse me, to bring that system into our digital frontline time and
attendance so that that will become a more routine and
ongoing process. So again, I'm eager
to have those folks be paid for the time that they have
already accrued, and then to be able to bring you that estimate in May.
Thank you.
Thank you, Dr. Prince.
And that's going to impact
the deficit amount-
Yes
... projected deficit amount.
Yes.
That the
city council
or city's reserve budget will need to
pay off for us on our behalf, and then there's some kind of
payback agreement we need to come to with them as well, right? So...
Yes.
We're-
Yes. Yeah. You're thinking it out loud and yes.
Yeah. Well, I'm just trying to be clear about what that means for-
It-
Yeah.
Yes.
It's, you know-
Yes. It would add to the deficit. That would need-
Yeah
... to be paid back, barring some other idea
or solution.
Mm-hmm.
The audit findings.
Can we have a... Next month, can we have
some kind of quick slide, what the findings were, what's been
addressed, and what remains outstanding to be addressed?
Mm-hmm. Yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
Yeah, we can do that.
Thank you.
And any other questions?
I do.
Member Monroe.
So we keep hearing a lot in the news, and
we're experiencing personally, that fuel prices are going up.
And
so are our buses diesel mostly?
They're mostly propane.
Oh, they're mostly propane. Okay.
Yeah. Mostly propane, and then some diesel, and then our vans take
gasoline.
Uh-huh.
Mm-hmm.
So because you mentioned some changes in transportation costs, but those are mostly
repairs then. We haven't-
Right. Yeah
... the changes that we've seen at the pump-
Yeah. Those are like transmissions and-
Uh-huh
... yeah.
So we're not seeing... The changes in fuel prices aren't affecting us
particularly.
Not a lot at the moment. I could see invoices roll in
with the propane charges a little bit. But yeah.
And
just for anybody who wasn't here last time it was explained,
Symetra is a firm that the city has engaged, an entity and
agency that they have engaged to help with
handling paid family leave, which is coming on blind.
That's right. Yep. So we are joining the city's blind.
Anyone hasn't heard that the last time-
Mm-hmm
... just wanted them to know what that is.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you. Any other questions?
Thank you.
Okay. Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
Next is the report of the policy committee.
We did not meet this month because there was so
much happening with the budget. But we do have the second read, which
will be an action item on the temperature standards for school
facilities.
And if nobody had any questions about that,
the report of buildings and grounds,
George, you're the only one who's here who can report on that.
And you and Member Feller are going to have to
talk with me about a new chair, but
do you have anything you want to say about your report on buildings and grounds?
No.
The next meeting was scheduled to be at Skillen
to get hands-on with the boiler and talk about that.
Great.
Thank you.
Next is 7.0, which is the consent agenda and
the consideration and action to approve the consent agenda items.
First, 7.1 is the approval of minutes from the regular meeting held on
March 9th. 7.2 is approval of the minutes from the executive
session of March 17th. 7.3 is the approval of the
minutes from the board workshop
held on March 23rd. 7.4, approval of the minutes from the
special budget meeting held on March 30th.
7.5 is approval of the minutes from the board workshop held on April
1st. 7.6, approval of the minutes from the special budget
meeting on April 2nd.
7.7, approval of the minutes from the executive session on April 6th.
7.8, approval of the minutes from the special budget meeting on April
7th.
7.9, approval of the minutes from the executive session on April
8th.7.10 is approval of the donations and
grants,
$1,050 scholarship from the Maine Community Foundation for a
graduating high school senior
who will be pursuing a certificate or a degree program in a
health-related field. $717 from the
South Portland Fire cheering for the South Portland Students Care Club
and used to purchase fresh food, produce, and other necessities to
keep Little Kitchen going during vulnerable times.
$500 scholarship from their revocable trust agreement
of Robert C. Roberge for a South Portland High School graduate.
$700 from the Ted Hellier Community Lacrosse
Grant to purchase sneakers and socks for student
athletes at South Portland Middle School,
and $1,500 from The Bullis Company to purchase cameras
for South Portland High School photography students.
So we would need a motion to approve
the consent agenda. Moved by Member Smith
and seconded by Member Holman.
Member Smith.
That was a nice little presentation of how much time we've gotten to spend
together. All these minutes. No, I have nothing else.
Yes.
Member Holman.
I would just say to thank everybody for the
donations and grants that were given to us.
If we total that up,
we have...
I'm trying to do really fast math here.
Almost 4,000.
Yeah. It's almost $4,000, correct, in
donations, and that's very generous, so I
want to thank people for making those donations.
And no further conversation or comment about that?
All those in favor of approving that motion?
And that's unanimous.
And then we have consideration and action to approve the temperature standards for
the school facilities.
I need a motion to approve.
Moved by Member Risch and seconded by Member
Holman.
Member Risch, do you want to say anything about it?
I believe the temperature standards came from a requirement for the
state-
Right
... and it was formulated in a committee I'm on.
I think it's pretty straightforward.
Yes. Thank you. Any other comments?
Seeing none, all those in favor of that motion?
And that is unanimous with the two students voting in favor as
well.
The next is 8.2, consideration and action to
request guidance and assistance from the
city council for one of the following options.
First,
increase taxes and direct increased tax dollars into the
'26, '27 school budget for the purpose of paying
for return of laid-off employees, and we would specify the
amount or the percent increase. Or the
second option, increase taxes and direct increased
tax
dollars into the contingency, specifically to seed
increased fund balance, and we would specify the
percent increase. Or third, to offset of shared
municipal services, the cost of SROs, the cost of
snow removal and sanding, et cetera, and specify the dollar
amount.
So would someone like to move that
motion in one of those three directions?
And we would take a second, so we could have a conversation.
Member Richardson.
Can
we talk about all three of them?
Well,
we have to put the motion on the floor to talk about it.
So one at a time?
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
And you can-
Okay
... pick any one of the three that you-
Can we start with the third one? Can I make a motion on the third?
Sure.
I'm sorry. I'm going to go out of order because I feel like-
That's okay. That's all right
... this one is a little easier to talk about.
Do you have a specified dollar amount?
Well, I have a question for-
Okay. So-
I misunderstood.
So we have to-
In order to get to that dollar amount.
Oh, okay. Okay.
I'm sorry.
No, no, no. That's fine. That's totally fine.
So
as I understand it, there has been a movement from the
city
to shift...
At one point, the city was kind of taking over
more of our infrastructure facilities costs, but there has been a movement to
shift that back to the school district.
Mm-hmm.
The motive, I'm not sure why.
I guess I could make a few assumptions on what the city's
sort of opinion at the time for thinking that that was a more
prudent way to separate the cost of
running a school versus the city.
And so I'm curious what those items
were and what the total amount would've been.
Because I think
it is very clear that the cost of public education is in
crisis.
And we have municipalities right across the border and
every
direction that are asking more of taxpayers right now.
And we are in a particularly,
we are in a rebuilding of financial stability
moment.
I've spent a lot of time speaking with
members of other school boards who are in Portland and
Brunswick specifically, who had to kind of create
arrangements with their city
colleagues on the... toTo kind of
support
the rebirth of financial stability for the school district.
I've shared that information with
our city manager,
with our city finance manager, with our mayor,
and also district staff here, and our chair,
because it demonstrates precedent for
an agreement that we are all in this together, and
there is actually
just sort of knowing that this is not a unique situation
for a school district to be in. So it's really hard to
specify. So,
knowing that that precedent exists,
and not knowing what the city is going to say to that proposal,
because I have yet not heard a response from anybody at the city on
this proposal.
I have spoken with many city councilors about it, and I have been told that if
there is precedent, then they will take that seriously.
So I'd like that to be the topic of some discussion with them
tomorrow or some sort of... And if it's me as a layman, not
a layman, I'm sorry, I said that, but if it's me as a public citizen making a
public comment tomorrow, I will. I will posit the question to them because I will
be there at the meeting.
But
we
have to rebuild back fund balance.
Yeah.
And we made some really aggressive cuts to this
budget that other municipalities
were not so aggressive.
We've had a constituent reach out to us to say,
"These other districts supported
their teachers
by asking more of their taxpayers."
We made a decision as a board to pay our
teachers more, pay our ed techs more.
There are consequences from that, and
this board has been shielding
the real cost of running this district from taxpayers for
years by dipping into fund balance.
So
anyway, I'm kind of getting into the numbers one and two.
But to me, number three is a no-brainer.
I don't know why we can't resurrect whatever
old model we had where they were doing the snow plowing for us and
we can put a time limit on it and say, "Give
us three years, and then we can see where we are."
But
I'm going to stop talking. But I don't know how to get to that number if we
need it. Do we
need a number?
Well,
I guess I would say that
the suggestion would be having a number so that we can talk about a
number, and we can talk about whether people want to
go and ask for that money or not. It's kind of
hard. It would be hard for me to support
something
without knowing what is it
people are-
Sure
... asking to support.
Well, we know that-
That's just-
Yeah, sorry. I-
I'm just one person.
Yeah.
No, I hear what you're saying. We know the cost of SROs, right?
Because it was like 220,000 or something.
Yeah.
So we know that.
And then there's this other-
Like snow plowing, 140 would do it.
Yeah. And then what else is
in the list of
costs that the city at one point was-
Mm-hmm
...
putting the bill for?
I don't have the list in front of me, but there are things the city does for
the school. Like, they help manage our bond payments.
They do things for us, for sure.
But I think George would have to speak a little bit more to
that. But I would agree, the idea floating in the air is
for the school to
pay the city for services that are rendered to the school.
That's a general idea. With the understanding that FY27 is
going to be really tough, and we'd get a break on that.
And just so I'm clear,
we have always paid for our own SROs, is that
correct?
Oh, that I don't know. I don't know if we always have.
I've never known of the city covering our SROs-
Mm-hmm
... in the school budget,
to my knowledge.
I don't have a history on that. Yeah.
So that would be an ask that we've
never had before. But just...
Mm-hmm.
Yeah. Member Holman.
Last year, we were actually, and
if you ever want to take a look at it, that's what I was looking at here.
Maine Public Radio published
a piece about
how South Portland was being asked to cut five million from our proposed budget.
And
we didn't really do that.
we're doing something very painful this year.
And we have excellent financial guidance finally, which we haven't
had.
There are some positions that I deeply would like to see restored.
I've talked about that already. In particular, I have strong feelings about the
related arts positions at the middle school because I think middle school
really needs those kinds of things.
Okay, Member Holman-
Go ahead.
Sorry.
Oh, I'm just getting there.
I'm just going to stop you.
Just get to the SROs. Okay?
Oh, okay.
I'm getting to the SRO. I'm not-
I'm just trying to, if we're going to-
It's a preamble. I understand
... stay focused on three, that's where we-
I understand.
Okay.
But,
I think the idea of if we could get the city to take over some things, I think
that's of interest. But-
The people who don't tend to come here to these meetings and speak to us are those
who are on fixed incomes and that type of thing.
It's a big deal to raise
taxes. They've been raised a lot because revaluation occurred,
because property taxes went
through the roof. Maybe property values went through the roof, and that
forces a state law kicks in, revaluation happens.
There are people whose property taxes went up 100%.
It's a lot to ask. I
hope
something like asking for the, whatever it is, 250K for SROs or
something we could possibly do. That would seem like a reasonable thing
to do.
So again, do we want to talk about number three?
And I'm
totally like, this isn't up to me. I'm just trying to find out where are we.
Do we want to talk about number three,
number two, number one, and does somebody have an
action so we can put an item on the table?
I have a question.
Okay.
I
intend to be there, of course, tomorrow as well.
The city is going to be looking at our budget.
Do we have to have something like this as required?
So let me tell you what's going to happen tomorrow.
All that's going to happen tomorrow is there is not going to be a
conversation between the board and the city
council. We're going to go in,
Abigail, Joe, and George will present the
budget.
It's a workshop, so
there's three minutes comment, and if people want
to comment, they can comment.
And as Member Richardson said,
and people can't really speak on behalf of the board.
If we take an action tonight for a particular
one of these items and a particular amount,
and the
council wants to know what the-- They'll
ask, and I'll respond with whatever it is we
decide, if we decide anything, and say, "This is
the request." They may respond to that tomorrow night.
They may not. It's not my
meeting.
But what I know is there's not going to be a conversation.
It's not going to be sitting around the tables like we've
had before and having a conversation with them.
That's what I know. Member Richardson.
Sorry. And maybe you said this, and I just got confused, but
for example, in something like number three,
are you presenting
that? Who's presenting that option if we approve of that as a majority
to-
It just-
How do we move that
concept forward?
If the
council asks what is the position of the board,
then I will respond with whatever
of those
we take for action or whatever
action we take. If we vote on it and there's a majority of people who want
to do one of these, I'll present that to the council tomorrow night.
I don't know what they're going to do with that.
But what I know is they're not going to have conversations.
Right. But your job is to-
Mm-hmm
... to say, "The board approved these three things last night or whatever, or two
things or whatever."
Yeah. Or, "The board's asking for this."
"The board's asking."
Yeah. Mm-hmm.
Right. Okay.
Well, I just heard 220,000 and 140,000
snow plowing and SROs. That's
360,000
in a shifting of costs.
I mean, again, I don't know why we need to pick a number because it sounds like--
I guess I would like to know if there's a way to figure out,
if that's roughly what they had been shouldering
or-
Well, as I said, they've never shouldered our SROs.
Well, I'm talking-- But you're forcing us to identify an amount.
Oh, no, no, no. I'm sorry.
Okay.
I'm just saying the 220-- I'm just saying they've never
shouldered that.
Oh, I know that.
That's all. Yeah.
I totally know that.
Sorry.
But I also-
I didn't write this motion.
Yeah. That's okay.
Yeah.
But there is precedent for the city covering certain infrastructure costs,
and
we don't know what that number historically has been.
Yeah, I have no idea.
Okay. Does anybody else want to say anything about this?
Because I feel like it's just me talking about this one.
No. I
would be ready to make a motion to ask for 360,000.
Great. Let's do it.
For number three.
Great.
So moved by
Member Smith and seconded by
Member Richardson
to
ask for an offset of shared municipal services, the cost
of the SROs, and the cost of snow removal and sanding, and
at the tune of 300 to the amount of
$360,000. So Member Smith.
Yeah, I think, all the points that Eleni's make, this is at least a
good starting point for us to have the conversation with the city
about kind of how to share these services going forward.
And so,
at least starting with that 360, it'd be good to hear from
them on their perspective.
Um, Member Richardson?
Nothing more to say on this one.
Does anybody want to say anything else?
I
have it. I think that there's not that much
they can do for us, but it'll be interesting to see if this is something they could
do for us.
So,
I'll give my opinion about why I don't support this.
For me,
I'm looking at the other two items, and there's
only one that I feel that I can support.
And so, I
support asking. So, the SROs,
it's just shifting cost. The
same thing with the 140,000. It's just shifting cost.
It's still taxpayers' dollars. It's the
same pool of money. It's just making our dollar
amount look less, which means that theirs is going to
look more. So, I don't
see... I
guess if we were to say that we think they should cover our
SROs, I
guess I would say, well, should the police department provide an
officer for WEX or
the main mall? It's a service we get,
so I believe it's a service we should pay for.
If we want to have the conversation about whether we should have
SROs at all, that's a different topic.
But for me,
it's still taxpayers'
dollars. So we're just shifting from...
It's stealing from Peter to pay Paul.
And,
so it's still asking for the... Taxpayers are still
paying for it. It's not like the police department has
$220,000 that they're just sitting on.
So, they have to then increase their budget by
220,000 because they're providing a service to us.
And I guess I just don't understand.
Yeah, I don't understand why,
if we're going to accept the service, why we wouldn't pay for it.
Can I say something?
Yeah, please.
Because we just had to let go of 74
people from our... I think. I can't remember the right number, but we
have 12% of our staff is gone, and the public
has been emailing us and city councilors begging
for help.
Mm.
So, and I think
the argument that was just made is more of in favor...
It sounds like what a city councilor argument might be, as opposed to
a school board argument.
And I'm very curious to hear what they have to say about it,
because
I know that
people are looking to them for help.
It's not unprecedented that the city has stepped in and
helped school districts in situations like this.
So, that's what I have to say about that.
Member Risch.
I'm kind of new to the board, but
I think it's worth asking something.
And I think number three is a reasonable level.
If it was up to me, I'd ask for 2% increase on number two, because I
think without a contingency, the more contingency we have, the more
compassion we can have next year. Even if something broke down,
the contingency is spendable.
It has less, we just say tethers, less constraints.
But-
So, just so I can get clear, are we asking for-
I'm just expressing my opinion. I'm not asking for any-
No, I'm just asking if we're... Well, I guess
we have to vote on number three first-
Yeah, I think three out of three
... and then if somebody wants to move inside.
I think three is a prudent thing to do.
Mm-hmm.
I understand where you're coming from, by the way. So, but it's worth asking.
Yeah. I-
I wish we had more open communications, and maybe we will in the workshop.
That's something for me to learn.
Member Holman.
There's nothing to stop the city from doing any of these things without our having
them come through as a motion, right?
I'm sorry. I don't understand.
In other words,
we could get there, and they could say amongst themselves, "You know what?
The school really needs more money.
We should tell them to ask for a higher percent." That could happen.
Absolutely.
That absolutely could happen.
Should we vote on number three?
Yeah.
Okay.
I'm just waiting to see if there's any-
Oh, sorry. I'm sorry
... further discussion.
Seeing any further discussion? Okay.
All those in favor of
number three, asking for 360,000?
Smith,
Richardson,
Risch, and Holman.
And opposed?
Okay. So,
that's the first item that we have passed, that passed with
four in favor and one opposed.
And we have
increased taxes and direct tax increase for the '26,
'27 school budget for the purpose of paying for
return of laid-off employees,
specify the percentage increase, or the second
increased taxes and direct increased tax dollars into
contingency specifically to seed increased fund balance,
specifically the percentage increase or dollar amount.
Thank you for putting that up there.
Anyone like to make a
motion?Member
Richardson.
Yeah. I think that
I'd like to see one and two move forward.
Can you give me one at a time so we can-
Sure
... take one at a time?
I'd like to see one move forward at a half a percent
increase,
which I think was 220. Yeah.
And then I'd like to see number two move for-
No. Let's do one at a time.
Sorry. Okay.
Let's do one at a time. So-
Is there a way to...
Sorry. May I ask Abigail a question-
Yes
... Chair? The breakdown that you showed earlier,
do you have the breakout of what the additional
add-on to taxpayers?
Nothing in the slides.
It's about 500 per 1%.
Oh.
At the very beginning.
Near that, yeah. Beginning slide.
Top. Back.
Next slide.
So, okay, half a percent adds-
But further than that, I'm wondering, what
does that look like
on a taxpayer's bill?
That's an illustration we've seen a lot.
I don't know.
The total 6% increase was something like
to a home of 500,000.
I think she's got that.
So
that would make each percentage...
My brain is not doing that.
I just to get back to you. But I'm working on it.
Yeah.
Okay, so we have move,
I think, we have move by Board Member Richardson-
You can do-
... on item one to increase taxes-
You can do both
... and direct-
You can just do both
... increase tax dollars into the '26, '27 school budget
for the purpose of paying for return of laid-off employees
to the tune of 1%. Do we have a second?
I'm sorry. I said half a percent.
She said half.
Half a percent.
Yeah.
I'm sorry. Did I say-
0.5.
You said one.
Oh, one. I'm sorry, 0.5%. Yeah, I'm looking at half a
percent. I don't know why I said that. I apologize.
And do we have a second for that?
So we don't have a second.
So that fails for the lack of a second.
So does anybody want to go to number two?
Rich.
Thank you.
Member Smith.
Yeah, I would make a motion to increase 1% on
number two.
So
increase taxes and direct increase tax dollars
into contingency, specifically to seed increased fund
balance
to the tune of 1%. It's moved by Smith.
Is there a second?
Seconded by Risch.
Member Smith.
I think
here I can make a support for a seed
increase
or fund balance increase and not a returning of laid-off
employees. Mainly
because when I look towards next year, I don't want us to
find ourselves in the same position, and I want us to get to a place as a
district where we can say to our employees that they're going to
have a position next year.
If we put ourselves into a higher increase this
year, as I think Abigail has shown pretty clearly, that's going to lead to a
higher increase next year.
And so I think with number two, we can get ourselves to some kind
of financial sustainability with that contingency and increasing the fund balance
in a way that I can support. I think Member Risch had talked about 2%
increase. I'm open to that as well.
I
hear the concerns that Member Holman has about folks on fixed
incomes and what this percentage means.
If it was my money, I would put it at 5%, but I
recognize that's a difficult ask for folks and a difficult ask for
city council. So...
Thank you. Member Risch.
I think it's important to ask.
I've heard in the past that they wanted to help, but they canceled it because
nobody asked. So if we can ask, and I'm supporting
contingency funds because of the
freedom to spend. It gives us more things that we can fix.
We can fix positions, we can fix roofs, we can do that sort of thing.
And in regards to the one or 2%, I have
a constituent who keeps reminding me how much the
local people have increased their
town budgets, and it's around 8%, maybe 7%.
I really do believe the school and what we do here is part of what makes
South Portland special, and we should at least ask.
Other
comments?
I just concur with what was just said.
And I do as well. I would say I support the
1%, and I support it going into contingency.
I think that we have
a loss of any savings, and I think
if we're going to ask for an increase to
tax dollars, if we ask for that,
um-And we're specifically putting it into
contingency that we're
saying we're trying to
start building our contingency again.
And so I support that as well. So
any other comments?
So all those in favor of asking increased taxes
and direct
the increased tax dollars into contingency, specifically to seed an
increased fund balance to the tune of 1%, all those in favor?
And that's unanimous.
Can I-- I'm sorry. Can I ask-
Yes, please.
... a question? So
let's say we go forward with tomorrow with a
1% proposal increase and
council's like, "Oh, are you sure that's enough?
We think it should be two." How does that work?
I'm thinking, yeah, not going to happen.
Right.
Yeah, no, but it could happen, right?
And
so
we can
come back and increase the budget,
to whatever extent the council thinks
that they can support, and that they would
pass it on to the voters, they'll tell us
that. I think they'll say that.
Again, tomorrow night is a workshop, so I don't know how much of this they're going
to entertain, but I'm going to report these two items
to them, that these are actions that were taken by the board tonight,
and that there was support for both of
these. They might say, "Well, we're willing
to absorb number three, but we don't think you should ask for more."
They could say, "We think you should ask for more, but we're not willing." I don't
have any idea what they're going to say.
And they could say, "I think both of them are reasonable."
And
so then we would be coming back with a 7% increase,
and
then potentially that they would absorb
$360,000 into their budget. Those two things
could certainly both happen.
But then we'd... Sorry, Jo, do you want to ask a-
Can I ask a-
Please.
In motions one and two, it's very clear to the administration
team what adjustments you would want us to bring back
to you for consideration. In the event that the city
council says they will fund
340 or whatever the dollar figure is in number three, it
would be helpful to the team if the board could give us clarity with
regards to, does that mean that you would then be looking for
the return of positions? Would those dollars that
we then did not have to spend on those services be directed to
contingency, or would it be to lower overall
tax burden? Because from that motion alone, any
one of those outcomes could be potential and again, if you're not
ready to take it up, just know that we would need that in order to bring you back
something.
So if I can just be clear, Dr. Prince, what you're asking is if
number two is clear, if the council
were to say, "We will absorb
360,000 and cover your snowplowing and your
SROs," you're looking to know, do we want
that to just be
reduced in our budget, period, or do we want it
to buy back-
Add it to con-
... some positions,
or
have that money go into contingency?
Correct. At some point, we would need that clarity to bring you another
proposal that packages everything together.
So at some point, we would need that.
And just to be clear,
if
you don't get that tonight,
the next time you'd be able to get that would be the 29th,
because that would be the next time we have a board meeting.
We wouldn't be able to give it to you outside of a public board meeting.
So-
Correct. I guess I had thought potentially the board could discuss
which of those three options. Obviously, we don't know what will happen at
council tomorrow night.
No, that's why I'm saying you're saying if we could decide it tonight.
You could decide one of those three directions to take, and the
reason that I say this is just to voice the urgency we have with
staff who we are waiting to move through the recall process
with. So the more we can know ahead of time,
then we don't have to wait a week for another meeting or an update.
So appreciate that consideration.
Thank you.
So the question, I think everybody understands it, but the question is, if the
council were to
approve, and again, the
challenge with number three is
they're in a budget workshop, so they're not able to take any
action. They're not able to take any
votes either. So they can't really
take a vote until they come into session.
So they could give us some general
sense, that, yeah, it looks like there's
more than four of them who are supportive of this
360,000.
And even though they would
then need to vote on that, we could in
fact give
Dr. Prince and Dr. Entwistle some guidance
about what we would want them to do with that money, should
we get it.
Right.
And we can have that conversation now.
Is it possible to make a motion on that now for-
Well, I think you can just-
... for discussion action?
Yeah.
Just talk about it, and then we can figure out whether we need
to make-
Yeah. For the same things that I had just discussed, I think putting it into
contingency
would make more sense for us for the long term and save
the headache of not knowing, I think, going forward.
Okay, so Tyland's position is to put it into contingency.
Where's anybody else?
I don't agree with that. I
want a
related arts program in our middle school, and I want to
have more support for our elementary staff. I don't know.
But I also didn't vote in favor of the budget the other night.
Okay, so Richardson wants to bring back
positions, basically. Is that what you're
saying?
Yes.
Yes. Okay.
Because, and
can I just say-
Oh, no. Oh, absolutely
... one thing about that? I
just think
we really have to be honest about the costs of running a
district that is
not taking on more risk,
and that is not taking away really
fundamental roles for the wellbeing of our kids,
like the related arts programs and middle school.
These are significant impacts to
the way that we operate our district, and every
other neighboring community is
passing that cost onto taxpayers in a more
realistic way.
And I know the city has been mindful
about
not moving forward with a Mahoney referendum or the police
station referendum because they know that we're in a bind over here.
And
if there's a way that we can work through the
shifting of infrastructure costs in a more temporary to permanent way
because we want to save some of these crucial
positions or the offerings in our district, and the support
to protect our teachers and staff,
then that's a conversation we really need to start having
with our community about the cost
of what these fundamental roles really mean.
I'm looking at
Holman, Risch, and DeAngelis for what you would like to do if
we were to get this 360,000.
I think I'd like to see
those related arts positions come back, but I don't know how much you
get in people for that amount of money.
People are really expensive.
Three people?
Three teachers.
Yeah.
So Member Holman, you're saying you'd like to bring back positions.
I'd like to bring back related arts positions, yeah.
Okay. Member Risch?
That's what I'm interested in.
Well, I think it's hard for me to determine which positions should be restored.
I would defer that to the
teachers.
But I guess what I'm asking, Member Risch, is-
I would vote for contingency, because again, I believe
that
given the state of some maintenance and
just our
operating expenses, we need contingency money.
So Member Risch
supports contingency. Member Smith supports contingency.
I also would support contingency.
So there's three positions for
contingency and
two for returning positions.
So we would be asking
for putting the money in contingency based on
this sort of informal
ruling here.
So I'm just trying to write a motion here, Member Smith.
So if the city were to give us $360,000
to cover
snow plowing
and SROs,
motion and action to
move that savings to contingency.
That motion is moved by
Member Smith and seconded
by Member Risch.
And all those in favor of that.
So there's-
Claire.
You're voting to have it go into contingency?
That's what we're voting on right now.
Yes?
No.
Oh, no. Okay.
Thank you.
So in favor is Smith, Risch, and DeAngelis.
And opposed?
Opposed.
Okay.
And opposed is-
Yeah
... Richardson and Holman.
So that motion passes, that the money would be to go into contingency.
Does it pass?
Okay.
So to answer
Member Richardson's question,
tomorrow night
the superintendent, assistant
superintendent, and
business manager will present the budget.
I will present items two and three as requests by
the board
that were both passed
andAnd we'll just
explain, and I have no idea what the council will do,
but that's where we are.
We are up to the vice chair transition
and nominations for the vice chair.
And
I would like to nominate Member Smith
to be the new vice chair. Is there a second?
And a second from Member
Holman.
I will just say that I
think Member Smith
will make a very good vice chair, and I think
you're very thoughtful, and
inquisitive, and interested, and committed.
And, I think you'll take this position and run with it, and
I appreciate that. And I appreciate your willingness to do it.
Member Holman, do you have anything you'd like to add?
Anybody else?
Okay, all those in favor.
Okay, and that's unanimous.
So congratulations, Member Smith.
And we are at second public comment.
Before I read this public comment, are there people...
Sarah, thank you. The board's public comment is an
opportunity
for the board to listen to opinions of the public that relate to school and
education matters.
The board is here to listen. Anyone wishing to speak will be asked to proceed to
the microphone and state your name and your town or city where you reside.
All questions will be recorded by the superintendent and chair with assistance
from other members of the board and will be answered at the end of
public comment to the extent possible.
If the answers are not available, someone will be assigned to
reply to you as soon as the answer is available, and you'll be given three
minutes to speak. There'll be no interaction between the public and the
board members, and additionally, no clapping, booing, or other interruptive
behavior will be allowed. Please consider
the impact of your comments as board meetings are broadcast
live, recorded, and posted on the city's website.
So,
yes.
Hi. Still Sarah Gay.
Still a citizen, educator, all that good stuff.
I actually just have a couple of questions.
And some of these came from members who have contacted me since our last
public comment, so thank you to those folks.
First question, who wrote the motion in item 8.2 on tonight's agenda, if
not the board chair?
I think a lot of us are struggling with how any new budgetary decisions
could be made on the fly
still,
without some consideration for data, stakeholder input, or dialogue.
A little bit surprising.
Would the district consider offering an exit interview to all staff who are
resigning or who have lost their jobs this year?
That certainly cannot be mandated, but it is not something that is routinely
offered, which I understand to be very common in other industries.
Regarding ed techs, if we are somehow able to find the money to subcontract
services or pay referral incentives, can we please just staff our SPED
classrooms appropriately? So my specific question is, will the cost
of subcontracting and incentives exceed the cost of
simply hiring people?
And then, I wasn't planning to come up, but here I am.
So for the fourth time, fifth, if you count an email to which I received no
response, I would like to ask each individual board
member, is our goal to provide an excellent education for all
learners the best we can provide, or is adequate good enough?
Members Richardson, Feller, and Holman have both publicly and privately asserted
that commitment,
quite dynamically so.
I believe Member Smith has as well. Thank you to that.
I'm troubled that
any elected school board member would hesitate to express their
opinion on that topic.
I wasn't going to ask that, but several people reminded me that it still had not
been answered. Thank you.
Thank you.
Meredith Diamond. Educator, community member, parent.
It's been incredible to see how this community has
galvanized over the past six weeks.
We have parents building tools to model attendance zones
and developing surveys to fill gaps in understanding created by
how the district has gone about this process.
We now know what this community is capable of, and I'm grateful for the
chance to have gotten to know my neighbors in this way.
I'm grateful for the board's recognition that the timeline for
reconfiguration was unrealistic.
I'm also concerned that at no point did we hear from the
board that lack of detail about reconfiguration
costs was a reason to pull back.
Next year, students of South Portland will once again return to schools
with fewer supports, larger class sizes, reduced
programming, and fewer opportunities than the students had before
them.
But not because we don't fund our schools, right?
To the contrary,
we fund our schools better than any other large district in the state of Maine,
and better even still than many districts in
Massachusetts.
We are removing supports and opportunities from our schools because
of negligent decision-making and financial mismanagement.
When is this going to stop?
Abigail, you give us hope. You have a lot of fans in the community.
Thank you for your hard work.
At our last meeting, there was a brief reference on a single slide about
contingency funds potentially needing to cover an
FY26 deficit.
Tonight, we learned that that could be as much as
$1.1 million, and our reserve is already in the
negativeWe've had a lot of discussion this month about the
importance of equity.
Financial solvency is one of the most powerful
strategies for equity.
Our most vulnerable and highest need students are those for whom the
stakes are highest when we make cuts like those that we're making right
now.
Thank you, Eleni, for digging into this issue and for seeking
creative solutions that aren't replays of what has been done
before. Your efforts are not going unnoticed.
I urge the rest of this board to also take seriously the way that your
choices, as well as those you've inherited, have created a
crisis of opportunity and support for the students of South Portland.
Please commit to greater accountability and more careful planning going
forward. Thank you.
Thank you, Meredith.
Good evening. My name is Charlie Fox, Evans Street.
I just have one thing. I'm a little bit concerned about
the vote you guys just took on voting against the
teachers pretty much, and voting putting the money back into the
reserve fund for 360,000 and kind of going
against the amount of teachers that have stood up here, parents,
faculty,
ed techs, everybody talking about how our special ed department has been
gutted this year, how the liberal arts department has been gutted,
having the robotics teacher come up here multiple times and
speak and how we can just kind of push that to the side
and think that we don't need them. Our gym
classes, our gym teacher in middle school is getting cut.
One of the biggest things we know is exercise for young
adults is more needed. Kids aren't getting as much
exercise as they used to, and not playing outside as
much, and these kids need it.
We're cutting places that families look at our
schools and look at reason why they want to move here because of the
schools. And if we want our schools to move up the ladder to
become some of the top schools in the state, we need to retain some of the
top teachers in the state.
We're not going to have teachers coming back by doing this.
We're going to lose teachers very fast.
I've already talked to teachers and talked to friends who are teachers in other
districts and families who've thought about moving here to South Portland, they
said they're not going to move here right now because of the uncertainty.
I'm a little concerned that we're just focusing on money for that and
not focusing on our teachers and the well-being of our students at the same time.
I really hope you guys can reconsider that and think about our students because
it is a major concern. Thank you.
Thank you, Charlie.
Good evening. Caroline Bowman, South Portland parent of two middle
school students, and I'm here again tonight to advocate for
keeping these really critical middle school-related arts positions.
Last Wednesday, I sent each of you a detailed email
regarding the
2027 budget. While I appreciate the two responses I
received, thank you to board members Richardson and Feller, the silence
from the rest of this board is deeply concerning,
especially given all of the current unknowns and questions that have
gone unanswered from the community over these past
meetings. The proposed cutting of middle school-related arts is
being lost in the noise of school closures.
But for my children and their peers, these programs are the heartbeat
of their school day.
Computer science, STEM, and phys ed are not extras.
They are the primary safety net and the source of belonging for students during
their most volatile developmental years.
The teachers you are removing are the heart and soul of our middle school
community.
Mr. Wetzel built a computer science program from the ground up,
making coding so exciting that he's opening doors to careers our kids
didn't even know existed.
Ms. Hellyer is a champion for our girls in STEM and a
dedicated coach who supports our athletes at every level.
She has truly built the high school girls lacrosse program, and we won't be able
to keep her there if she doesn't have a job in the district.
Mrs. Watson is the reason so many of our students even have access
to the equipment they need to play sports.
She is constantly going above and beyond to bridge the gap for our families.
And Mr. Lenson developed our middle school level unified
basketball program,
ensuring that students of all abilities have the opportunity to
be part of a team.
My own son, currently an eighth-grader, chose to take phys
ed every single semester of his time at South
Portland Middle School.
With these proposed cuts,
this will no longer be an
option.
And my son has plenty of other opportunities for
athletics, staying active. He also plays on the middle school
basketball team, but many of his classmates do not have the same
opportunities.
And by cutting opportunities for phys ed in half,
for many students, you're taking away their only safe time during the day to
be active or play. Something that the data clearly supports is
important for healthy development at this age.
When this board talks about access and equity, please remember,
these are the very real, very human cuts you are making.
By eliminating these positions, you aren't just balancing a budget.
You're dismantling the very programs that keep students engaged and connected to
school. We are being asked to accept a lower standard of
education for our middle schoolers with no evidence-based studies on
how these cuts will impact student mental health or long-term achievement.
Thank you.
Thank you, Caroline.
Hi, Ed Cobb, Romano Road.
My daughter actually went through the South Portland school system.
I will say that I did send her to private school at Waynflete during middle
school.
She's going to graduate from college in about less than a month,
and I'm a pretty proud parent because of that.
But I will say this, when she went to Dyer Elementary School, there was
26 kids in her classroom,
and somehow or another, she managed to go to college. I don't know how.
Some sort of miracle, maybe.
I've watched these school board meetings online.
I at one time thought about coming down and speaking and sort of thought better of
it because I didn't want my emotions to get the best of me.
I think it's a little,
I don't know, disrespectful the way this board has been treated in
some cases, harassing phone calls.
I don't think that's the community that we want to be or live in, certainly not a
community I want to live in. But I will state out the basic math
of these budget increases from the city and from the school board.
And I get it, the school department takes up, roughly speaking, 60%, 62%
of the total budget,
maybe a little more, maybe a little less.
But just based on the average home in South Portland,
taxes right now are $6,266 roughly on
an average home. If you do basic math,
which I can do, and I didn't go to college, actually,
at 6% a year, in less than a decade, the average
homeowner in South Portland is going to have a tax bill of $10,000.
And I
get it that you want the best for your kids in education, I really do, and I get it
so much that I literally took $90,000 out of my own personal
retirement account, to which I have nothing left in my retirement
account, and paid for middle school to send my daughter to Waynflete.
The Constitution... Or not the Constitution, but the state says adequate.
I'm sorry that maybe there's local taxpayers who can't
afford to have a $6,000 or, in less than a decade, a
$10,000 tax bill.
I doubt very highly
that there are many homeowners not coming to South Portland because of the
district. I think the issue is 26 houses, stick-built houses,
or not even stick-built, that includes condos, for sale.
The least expensive stick-built house in South Portland right now is
$399,000 for 650 square feet. I
know because my father, at 80 years old, thought about moving to
South Portland from Naples. He looked at the house today.
650 square feet, $399,000, and the tax bill's
almost $4,000 on that house.
At some point, there's got to be a balancing act here by
what adequate means and what taxpayers can bear
because I don't think many in this community and in this room can write a check for
$10,000 for property tax bills.
That's three minutes.
And I appreciate your time. Thanks so much.
Perfect. Thank you, Ed.
Morgan Kerr.
I just drove down here.
I just actually got information from
a friend who sent me article
online saying that the board is going to consider
voting to
recall reconfiguration, and I just want to talk about that for a second.
So I'm a Kayler parent, but more importantly, I'm a South Portland
parent.
And I think that is the important part, and I think
we're really missing an opportunity to not just be Kayler parents or Brown
parents or Small parents or Dyer
parents or Skillman parents, but South Portland parents.
And I think if you started
listening to
other voices, not maybe the loudest ones in the room
or
the ones who are getting the most air time, that there was movement
to really support reconfiguration.
And I'm really, really proud of the way the Kayler community
has rallied around a really difficult situation,
and we're making positive strides to not only make this
work for our kids,
but for every kid in South Portland.
And
I don't know if we were really afforded that by a lot
of other people.
So I really appreciate everyone who has stepped
up and
being like, "How can we make this work?
How can we be a community to make this work?"
And,
if it was any other school that was closing down, I'd be the first one
to say, "Let's reconfigure," because it's not just what's best for my kid,
it's what's best for all kids. Thank you.
Thank you, Morgan. Thank you.
Vladimir Kochan again. I would just like
to put a voice in the pro-tax camp.
With inflation what it is,
if you want quality services, you have to keep up with the cost of living.
We need to be able to pay teachers a living salary. We want to have good services.
I say don't be afraid of the voter. Don't be afraid to put things on the ballot,
like tax increases. If they say no, then we know where the voter stands.
But they might say yes,
and they might say yes to a larger amount of a tax increase than you might
anticipate. And I recognize, I had a really good conversation with
Rosemarie. I recognize that there's constituents for whom
these tax increases might mean that they have to potentially change their
lifestyle or even move out of South Portland.
But everyone in South Portland is a voter or is a constituent,
and I think we should give them a voice and let them vote with their wallets and
with their votes. Thank you.
Thank you, Vlad.
Lauren.
Lauren Shapiro, Deak Street.
Thank you for pausing for more thought, more process, and giving the
community the power to build this.
But Kaler deserves to be at this table, too.
In regards to closure, we also need to be clear about class size.
It is one of the strongest indicators of student achievement and has a
significant impact on the learning environment for both students and
staff. This is one of the least discussed, but most
concerning change, and it is not supportive to the realities of the
classrooms as they exist today. What is the plan
to address the increased class sizes, and is this plan supported
by staff?
We should also recognize the importance of retaining and supporting
male educators and BIPOC staff,
particularly where they are underrepresented.
Representation matters. It broadens the understanding of
caregiving, teaching, and leadership, and reinforces that
empathy, structure, and support are not defined by gender or
race.
It strengthens school culture by providing diverse role models,
deepening belonging, and expanding what students believe is
possible for themselves and others.
Please consider restoring these positions rather than removing
them. In regards to special education,
the data presented was alarming as is,
but even more so because I'm told these interventions
typically occur only after situations have escalated
significantly,
often involving serious harm or risk to staff and students.
Since restraint and seclusion do not account for all the dangerous
incidents in the classroom, it is clear that the dangerous
incidents are under-reported.
That leads to broader questions. How accurate is our
data on dangerous incidents if not everything is
consistently reported?
Where can the public access comprehensive incident reporting,
not just restraint and seclusion numbers, but all forms of
violence involving staff and students, including dangerous behavior
forms?
On the budget side, what are driving the rising costs?
How might programs change as schools shift?
And how does our spending compare to neighboring districts?
30 seconds.
Lastly, can the director present this information at the next board
meeting and take questions publicly?
Because transparency in this area is essential. Thank you.
Thank you, Lauren.
Anyone else who would like to speak for public comment?
Seeing none,
second public comment is closed. Thank you.
We are up to
answer
some questions. So the first question was asked by Sarah
Gay, who asked who wrote item 8.2.
And what I can tell you is how the agenda is put together.
The agenda's put together with usually the chair
and the superintendent, and often the vice-chair.
The vice-chair has been in many meetings with me.
We go over the items that are
necessary, that are going to take action, or that
are going to be reported, and then
we rough out what the
action item will be,
and then it's finalized and
sent to the
chair for final approval. The
superintendent and I did talk about items one and two,
and item three was recommended by the finance
director,
is my understanding.
Is that correct?
Yeah. Okay. So,
that's why I was unfamiliar with item three, because I was
not a part of that.
Anyway, that was the first question.
This question would have to be to the superintendent.
It was asked, could we offer exit interviews
to all people leaving?
I would say that
offering exit interviews to anyone leaving is a good thing to do.
It's an important thing to do, and it should be part of any
process.
But particularly those who are leaving at this
time, it would be a good
ability for us to collect some data and reflect on what that
data tells us.
Thank you. I think the third question, and I might not have gotten this
correct, so maybe somebody else got it, but I think it was
asking, does subcontracting of ed techs cost
more than hiring ed techs? Am I
correct on that question?
Yes.
Okay. I don't have the answer to that.
We can touch on that
one.
Yeah.
So I think as Director Cat Cox said, we want
to be in partnership in thinking about how to improve
retention and staffing for our ed tech roles.
I think we have brainstormed in the past with other
associations, as she mentioned with
transportation, ways to increase
an employee incentive program. Certainly, we want to
honor all of our contracts and work with our
associations. Subcontracting
has real dangers, and we are aware
of those. I think, though, we want to be creative and
around the table with our association partners to
think about how we can staff for those, and again, maybe how
we can incentivize for additional training.
We took one small step with this year's contract with the safety care payments,
but certainly would imagine that our partners have other ideas on how we can
continue to build those sort of incentives for the highest
trained workforce, so that folks feel that they
have all the knowledge and skills for their positions.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
I think the next question was
asking board members
what our purpose was of education.
I don't know if people are prepared to answer that question or...
It was Sarah's question about-
Okay
... is adequate good enough?
Mm-hmm.
The answer for me is no, adequate is not good enough.
I agree.
I agree as well.
It was an oversight that I didn't answer the question. I'm sorry.
It was an oversight that I didn't either.
I think that what was pointed out tonight is that's
what the state statute reads, I believe,
is that we are only required to provide adequate.
But I think in my view, and
I'm just guessing other peoples up here, that our goal is
always to provide the best education we can for students.
Whatever
funding we have that can provide the best education
would be our goal.
I didn't get any other questions. Did anybody else get
any?
The final speaker asked some questions about
data, specifically on dangerous incidents.
Oh, okay.
And if that is publicly available, and if there's anything beyond
just seclusion.
Right. Comprehensive
data is what she-
Yeah
... suggested.
Is there a place where that can be seen?
And I don't know. Was that in relation to special education?
Yeah.
Yeah. I don't know.
Sure. There is some data available on the
state's
Every Student Succeeds Act page that we can make sure
that there's sort of a clear overview of how to get to that
information, and then if the board is requesting additional
information,
we certainly can work to prepare that.
But there is on the main DOE, there's certain reporting
fields that we have to
share data with, and then that gets published statewide.
So we can make sure that the board and public know how to navigate to that next
time. If you also just Google ESEA Dashboard
Maine, you will get there as well.
Thank you.
Did anybody have any other questions that they saw?
I didn't hear any others.
Okay.
So I think we've answered all questions. We're at school board communications.
Does anybody have anything they'd like to
say or add or announcements they want to
make?
Yeah. And I
think the goal was to continue with listening
sessions. Is it the plan, Joe, to keep the schedule
as it presently is for continued listening sessions?
Yes.
Okay.
So those listening sessions, which are still posted, are
available for people to continue.
Our goal is that, as I said, there would be an
action at the April 29th meeting.
But in the meantime,
continuing the action, and once the
grade level configuration committee is formed,
that will begin the process to
continue as well,
to continue the work of reconfiguration, but just providing more
time. So,
yeah.
Can I?
Yes, please.
Is it possible to have some kind of proposal
for
how Kaylor community can
understand what's next? Like how the next steps look for them,
because we now have a different timeline.
Hopefully one that
can
be influenced by this board in terms of
how to be careful with placement and identifying the
appropriate boundaries, and if it's like a phase one of reconfiguration,
such that there's no multiple transitions for those students-
Right
... if we're looking to reconfigure in the next year.
We've had a lot of really thoughtful ideas come to us,
but with actual concrete data that
I haven't been able to crunch those numbers, but it would be nice to know
how close those proposals are, such that they are actually possible.
So I think to go with what Member Richardson is saying,
it would seem that when we do some discussion on the
29th, that there be some plan of action
that the board can see, and that Kaylor
parents and families and students and staff
can see with regard to how that's going to move forward.
Does that make sense?
Sure.
Dr. Prince.
I would just say that we would be happy to bring some thoughts on the
29th, recognizing that we have school vacation week next
week. And, yes, I had the opportunity to do the
listening session with Kaylor staff and with Kaylor families, and there were a lot
of comments. It
feels more realistic to say that we could deliver on a process for the
29th, but that that would still need Kaylor's voice on it.
And again, I just don't know what availability families have next week to engage
with us, so...
Okay.
Yeah. I think the goal just being to continue to
be providing for us what's happening and in as timely a
manner as possible, and I think
everybody knows that. Member Holman.
I just want to say that we've had a great deal of comment from a lot of
educators about the pace of
reconfiguration. And this is not a
criticism, but however, I do want to just say, in my mind, I
heard the word halt referred to on reconfiguration, and I don't
envisage any halt. I think we're talking about a change in pace, and I think that's
what is intended to be meant.
Was intended.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And so-
Thank you for saying that
... but I just-
I really meant halt this process right now.
I understand what, yeah.
But I don't mean-
Yes
... halt the plan for reconfiguration.
Right. Because I really do think it's the way for us to go.
And I want to thank in particular
Morgan
Kerr for your comments. I thought that was
elegant to the way you referred to
kind of being a South Portland parent. I thought that was elegant.
Thank you for that.
Thank you, and thank you everyone.
If there are no further comments, without objec-
You know, I just want to say one more thing, too.
Sorry, I do have one more thing to say.
Just that it's been a huge amount that we've heard from people.
And it's amazing what fluent writers we have, how people
have write very... So I just apologize, anyone I didn't get to, it's not by
intent, but it's been
hard to keep my job and do this with all the things we've got, so I
apologize for that.
Thank you, and without objection, this meeting is
adjourned.